<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A soveraign remedy against atheism and heresy. Fitted for the vvit and vvant of the British nations / by M. Thomas Anderton.</title>
            <author>Anderton, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 208 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 87 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08370</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3110A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R172305</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">64550865</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 64550865</idno>
            <idno type="VID">184324</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08370)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 184324)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2858:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A soveraign remedy against atheism and heresy. Fitted for the vvit and vvant of the British nations / by M. Thomas Anderton.</title>
                  <author>Anderton, Thomas.</author>
                  <author>Hamilton, Frances, Lady.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 139, 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. 1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published after his death and dedicated to the Lady Frances Hamilton by her humble Chaplin E. G."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christianity and atheism --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Atheism --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Sarah Wingo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:184324:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184324:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SOVERAIGN REMEDY AGAINST ATHEISM and Hereſy. <hi>FITTED FOR THE VVIT and vvant of the British Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY M. THOMAS ANDERTON, aliás BARTON.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>PVBLISHED AFTER HIS DEATH, and Dedicated to the Lady Frances Hamil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, By her humble Chaplin E. G.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An. 1672.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:184324:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184324:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST ILLVSTRIOVS LADY THE LADY FRANCES HAMILTON.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>England your natiue ſoil, once ſo much celebrated throughout all Chriſtendom for an Iſtand of Saints and Angels, is novv cenſured, euen by its ovvn Parliament, as a Nurſery of <hi>Atheiſm</hi> and <hi>Hereſy,</hi> and therfore that great Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatiue of the Nation is no leſs ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitous
<pb facs="tcp:184324:3"/>for a cure, than ſenſible of a diſeaſe ſo dangerous and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue not only to the ſoul, but to the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy politik of the Commonvvealth. And yet either our misfortune or their miſtake hath renderd all reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies hitherto ineffectual. This Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, <hi>MADAM,</hi> compoſed by <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Thomas Barton</hi> (vvhoſe Vvit muſt be admired ſo long as there vvill be any in the vvorld) vvas found vvith his <hi>Geometry</hi> in Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land (vvhere he had deſigned to print both) and beſtovvd upon me by one that underſtood not the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish language, nor the ualue of his <hi>Preſent.</hi> In my iudgment 'tis one of the beſt <hi>Antidotes</hi> againſt the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual plagues vvervvith England is infected. I publish it under your Lad<hi rend="sup">ps</hi> patronage (and beg pardon for
<pb facs="tcp:184324:3"/>doing ſo vvithout your Knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) becauſe you are not only a perfect Pattern of that ancient Faith and Virtue vvhich it aſſerts, but a particular Inſtance, and a conuincing Proof, that Hereſy and Atheiſm haue not ſo vvholly chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the nature of old England, but that euen novv it produceth Angels.</p>
            <p>I Knovv, <hi>MADAM,</hi> theſe Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ths vvill offend your modeſty and Humility, your greateſt care being to conceal your natural and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Gifts, and to eclipſe to the eyes of men your ſpiritual exerciſes and deuotion, feigning to be as vvell pleaſed vvith the vvorld, as the vvorld is vvith you. But that vvhich hath exalted you aboue the vvorld, and (I hope) vvrit your na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me
<pb facs="tcp:184324:4"/>in the book of life, is your extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Charity. You are not in the liſt of thoſe vvho hope to be ſaued by charitable indiſcretions; No, <hi>MADAM,</hi> Prudence directs your almes as vvell as your other actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: Humor hath no share in your di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributions, Vanity no influence upon your liberality; partiality no ſuffrage in the choice of the poor you relieue. You ſtretch your piety to the ſupport of merit (vvhereſoeuer it is) iniured by Fortune; and to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Virtue oppreſſed by perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution. And though you do it vvith ſo great caution as to diſguiſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural Charity vvith that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ayr of generoſity, ſo natural and peculiar to your ſelf; yet your deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ut deſign is diſcouered, and your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard before God, as vvell as the
<pb facs="tcp:184324:4"/>relieued perſons obligation to you, infinitly multiplied. Pardon me, <hi>MADAM,</hi> if I treſpaſs upon your Reſeruedneſs, and chooſe rather to incurr your Lad<hi rend="sup">ps</hi> diſpleaſure, than concurr to preiudice Mankind, by depriuing it of ſo great an encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement to Virtue as the Knovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of your perfections. I ſpeak, <hi>MADAM,</hi> of thoſe hidden in your ſoul, not of thoſe vvhich shine outvvardly, and can not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed, as your matchleſs beauty, and charming graces. Theſe, <hi>MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DAM,</hi> are but fading and falla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Ornaments that ſet out Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality in a deluding dreſs, vvith gay and liuely colours, vvhich a litle tyme vvill deface; the ſad fate of the greateſt beautyes, as vvell as of the faireſt flovvers.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184324:5"/>
            <p>I need not inculcat this Truth to your Lad<hi rend="sup">p</hi>. tis ſo deeply printed in your ſoul, that others are odious to you, if they but touch upon any of thoſe rare qualities vvhervvith <hi>Nature</hi> (by ſtraining its povver to the utmoſt) hath made you a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of itſelf, and plac't you in the vvorld as a Model, not to be imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated, (much leſs paralelled) but to be admired, euen by thoſe moſt emulous and enuious of your ovvn ſex vvhich fancy themſelues ought to be adored by ours. But that vvhich moſt ſurpriſeth the vvorld is, that ſo enuied a Miracle of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as your Lad<hi rend="sup">p</hi>. could neuer yet be cenſured or obſerued of hauing any Kind of inclination to be admired or applauded. This is a Miracle of Gods grace, and an effect of that
<pb facs="tcp:184324:5"/>natural modeſty and eminent ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor vvherby you alvvayes haue preſerued your unſpotted reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the tvvo moſt dangerous Courts of Chriſtendom; to both vvhich you are in this particular the beſt example, as in all other things the greateſt Ornament. This auerſion to your ovvn prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes is the only reaſon vvhy I da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re not mention the great Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and high Alliance of your il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Family, the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and uſual Ingredient in all <hi>Dedicatories.</hi> I should uentu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re though to ſay ſomthing of your acute VVit, profound iudgment, agreable humor, gracefull utteran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, becomming behauior, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet conduct, but that theſe are abuious and obſerued by all the
<pb facs="tcp:184324:6"/>VVorld, and particularly by the greateſt Court and beſt Iudge ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; vvhich giues your Lad<hi rend="sup">p</hi> this Character, That you are an exact English Beauty, naturaly adorned vvith all the graces of France, and an abridgment of the pureſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of both Nations. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe euen this authentik and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable Teſtimony is not grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to your Lad<hi rend="sup">p</hi>. and that it is impoſsible to ſpeak any truth of you vvithout commending and offending you, I am forc't to cut off a long <hi>Panegyrik</hi> of your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued praiſes, and conclude vvith this one (vvhich I hope vvill not be offenſiue) that you are the only perſon vvho thinks you are unvvorthy of that litle I haue ſayd heer, or that can
<pb facs="tcp:184324:6"/>command me to ſay no more but that I am vvith all reality and reſpect,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Lad<hi rend="sup">ps</hi> moſt obedient and moſt humble ſeruant. E. G.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:184324:7"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ith no leſs humility than charity I will propoſe my thoughts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Atheiſm and Hereſy of our Countrey, hoping that if my ſenſe differs from that of others, I shall not be blamed for offering and ſubmitting my opinion to better iudgments. I shall endeauor to ground mine upon Scripture and reaſon. Scripture compares Hereſy to that crafty ſerpent, which deceiued our Mother <hi>Eue</hi> with the curioſity of Knowing the cauſe and reaſons of Gods reuelations; perſuading her that human vnderſtandings ought not be ſatisfied with any thing leſs than cleer euidence, as if it were beneath men to ſubmit to authority. Vvhen our curioſity and pride preuails with us to contemn the teſtimony and tradition of the Church, and to preferr our priuat opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions before the publik doctrin and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe therof, and that we are obſtinat in that way, we becom heretiks, and in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of time Atheiſts: So filth and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption becoms firſt a creeping ſerpent, and afterwards a flying Dragon. For, as
<pb facs="tcp:184324:7"/>this Vermin is engendred by the heat of the ſun in marish grounds, and dirty ſinks, ſo Hereſy and Atheiſm haue their firſt <hi>being</hi> from the influence, which heate of paſſion, height of pride, and ſenſual plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures haue vpon vicious ſouls. Theſe wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in the mire of ſin, and ſucking up its venom, beget the priuat ſpirit, which is a ſerpent that with hiſſing whiſpers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects the brain by asking why God gaue men their ſenſes, if it was not to be direc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted wholy by them in iudging euen of myſteries of Faith. And though God tells us that the euidence of ſenſe is fallacious, when it agrees not with his word, as it proued when <hi>Eue</hi> taſted the forbidden fruit, yet Heretiks deſpiſing that truth, and imitating her example, prefer the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent or the priuat ſpirits ſuggeſtions, and their own appetit before Gods reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and interpret the Scriptures after a new manner, contrary to the teſtimony, tradition, and practiſe of the Church, in fauor of liberty and ſenſuality.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hereſy</hi> hauing thus ſlighted Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal authority, and the ſupernatural ſigns or Miracles of the Roman Catholik Church, as fables or frauds of intereſted perſons; and finding no ſigns or ſeales
<pb facs="tcp:184324:8"/>of a Deity in any other Congregation, it begins to doubt of Gods prouidence; and after many windings and turnings from one Sect to an other, deuoring moſt groſs abſurdities, euen againſt the Diuinity of Chriſt, and immortality of the Soul, it growes at length to be a Dragon, which armed with ſcales of obſtinat incredulity, and wingd with unbridled liberty and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, flyes at the Deity itſelf, like that ſeuen headed Beaſt of the Reuelations. So that Atheiſm is nothing but ouergrown He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy, as the Dragon is an ouergrown ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. Both agree in making ſenſuality the ſoul of man, and the rule of Faith. The Heretik, by ſubmitting his Faith and Soul to euidence of ſenſe againſt Gods war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and word; the Atheiſt by maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning men haue no Faith or ſoul but ſenſe. This laſt error ſeemes to ſom the more iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious, it being moſt euidently certain, that if there be a ſpiritual Soul, it muſt be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior and ought to command ſenſe, cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing its inclinations as foolish, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting its euidence as fallacious.</p>
            <p>Againſt this vermin and venom of Atheiſm and Hereſy I haue prepared the <hi>Antidot</hi> I heer preſent you with; its chief <hi>ingredients</hi> are ſtrength of reaſon, and
<pb facs="tcp:184324:8"/>
               <hi>ſupernaturality</hi> of Miracles; it is as natural for reaſon to ſubmit to Miracles, as it is for ſenſe to ſubmit to reaſon. For, what greater violence can be offered to Reaſon, than to rebell, or reſiſt againſt authority, ſignd by Gods hand and ſeale, <hi>Miracles?</hi> Or to deny a <hi>Deity</hi> and <hi>ſpirits,</hi> becauſe they com not under the <hi>Kenning</hi> of our ſenſes? Is it not againſt the firſt principles of reaſon and morality, to iudge otherwiſe of things and perſons, than they ſeem to be, when neither the word of God, nor any thing elſe appears to the contrary? Though we do not ſee <hi>ſpirits,</hi> or the Deity, yet we ſee effects a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the ſphere and power of <hi>bodyes,</hi> and <hi>Nature,</hi> which can not be attributed to any other cauſes but Spirits, and a Deity. So that we muſt grant the exiſtence of theſe, or maintain an impoſſibility, which is, that there can be an effect without a cauſe. Vvhat effect this <hi>Antidot</hi> will work upon the minds of the Readers, God only Knowes. I haue endeuored to expreſs my thoughts in the cleereſt termes I could, and in ordinary English the higheſt my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of Chriſtianity. Others may excell in the quaintneſs of expreſſion; I deſire no ſuch commendation; neither is that
<pb facs="tcp:184324:9"/>manner of writing ſo proper in matters of <hi>Faith,</hi> which limits our <hi>vvords</hi> as well as our <hi>opinions.</hi> And though the latitude were greater, I should chooſe thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions which are beſt vnderſtood, my deſign being to inform all ſorts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. Yet I would haue our <hi>vvits</hi> Know (and I hope they will find it ſo by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience) that Atheiſm and Hereſy, how new and ſubtile ſo euer, may be ſolidly confuted in ordinary and old English.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:184324:9"/>
            <head>A SOVERAIGN REMEDY againſt Hereſy, and Atheiſm, Fitted for the wit and want of the British Nations.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>OF THE EXISTENCE, VNITY, and Trinity of God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. Is there any ſuch thing as God? I knowthere is ſuch a notion, and that men fancy (when they ſpeake of God) an vnlimited being, including in it ſelf infinit excellencies, and all perfections. My que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is, whether this Deity of all and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit perfections be only a meer notion, or a real obiect?</p>
               <p>A. it is a real obiect.</p>
               <p>Q. How proue you that: for, we haue notions not only of things that do not exiſt, as <hi>Vtopia,</hi> but of things that can not poſſibly exiſt, as <hi>Chimeras, Centaures,</hi> &amp;c. How therfore wil you make it appeare that the notion of an infinitly perfect Deity is not the bare notion of an impoſſibility?</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:184324:10"/>
               <p>A. Many proofes there are of Gods real exiſtence, but (in my opinion) the cleereſt of all muſt be grounded vpon the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience euery man hath of his own nothing. For, the only thing we know cleerly euen of our ſelues is, that we do exiſt and are our ſelues, and yet that there was a tyme we did not exiſt, nor were our ſelues, or (which is the ſame) that we were nothing.</p>
               <p>From hence neceſſarily follow theſe concluſions. 1. that we can not haue our being or exiſtence from our ſelves; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that which at any tyme hath bin no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, or did not exiſt, can no more giue a being or exiſtence to it ſelf, then nothing can produce ſomthing. 2. that there muſt of neceſſity be ſomthing which did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes exiſt, otherwiſe nothing did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce all things. 3. that the ſomthing which did alwayes exiſt, muſt include all and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit perfections; becauſe hauing its being or perfection only from it ſelf, as none could giue it a being but it ſelf, ſo none but it ſelf could ſet a limit to its being or perfections; and that thing muſt haue bin naturaly auers to it ſelf, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, not it ſelf, which would wave, hinder, or enuy its own happineſs, or its hauing all perfections.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:184324:10"/>
               <p n="4">4. As it is impoſſible that a thing which hath its being from it ſelf, should want, or waue any perfection, ſo is it impoſſible there should be two or more diſtinct things infinitly perfect. Becauſe that which is the ſource of its own being, muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily include in it ſelf all being, or all perfections; ſeing there can be no cauſe or reaſon why it should haue one perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and not all, vnleſs you wil fancy that a thing before it exiſts, or is any thing, can limit it ſelf, or (out of a pik to it ſelf) would pick and chooſe out of infinit per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections only ſuch as Atheiſts attribute to that which they call <hi>Nature.</hi> If therfore all perfections muſt be included in that one thing which hath its own being from it ſelf, no other thing of infinit perfections can be as much as fancied to be diſtinct from it. Therfore it muſt be the ſame: and conſequently there can be but one thing, or one God, including in it ſelf, or iden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying with it ſelf, all perfections. So that you ſee how little wit Atheiſts do shew, in denying a Deity of infinit perfections; becauſe they muſt either grant it, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs that we men (or any thing els) when we did not exiſt, and were nothing, did or could produce our ſelues. Or that this world,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:184324:11"/>with all its imperfections, is God; or that, the world before its exiſtence, when it was nothing was alſo ſomthing; and ſo againſt the firſt and cleereſt notions and princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of mankind, it muſt be ſayd, that <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> hath not only proportion with <hi>ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</hi> but alſo that <hi>nothing</hi> and <hi>ſomthing</hi> haue the ſame properties, and work the ſame effects, and by conſequence that there is no difference or diſtance between ſuch contradictions, as nothing and ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, being and not being, exiſtent and not exiſtent.</p>
               <p>Q. I ſee that the exiſtence and vnity of God is much more cleere than Atheiſts pretend; but me thinks the ſame argument wherby you proue Gods vnity, conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des the impoſſibility of the Trinity: for if there can not be two or more things infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitly perfect, it muſt be granted that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Father, ſon, and holy Ghoſt, are not things, or <hi>beings</hi> diſtinct one from the other; or if they be, that they are not infinitly perfect.</p>
               <p>A. To this queſtion, or obiection there are two anſwers. The firſt and beſt is, that God were not infinitly perfect, if ſuch imperfect creatures as we know our ſelues to be, could comprehend his excellencies
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:184324:11"/>and myſteries. And though as rational crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, we ought (euen in what we belieue) be directed by reaſon, yet that reaſon which is our guide, can lead us no further in many things than to perſuade vs ſubmit to credible authority, which is the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of a Church or Congregation au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentikly authoriſed by God to beare witneſs that he reuealed ſuch and ſuch myſteries. Though the truth of theſe my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries be not intelligible or viſible to our human, vnderſtandings, it were want of vnderſtanding to doubt of them, or to deny them: becauſe there is not any one truth more cleer to vs, nor more obuious (by vndeniable experiments) to all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind than this, that there are many truthes wherof our human vnderſtandings can giue no reaſon. Now if this be ſo in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and ordinary things, why should we preſume or pretend that the myſtery of the Trinity is not true, becauſe we forſooth, can not comprehend its truth?</p>
               <p>The ſecond anſwer is this, the Father, the ſon, and holy Ghoſt, haue but one being, or nature, common to all three, and therfore they are equaly powerfull, equaly wiſe, equaly good, and eternall, and by conſequence but one God. But becauſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:184324:12"/>this diuine nature, or eſſence hath three different manners of being, and that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of theſe three manners is identified with, and inſeparable from the Deity, though diſtinct one from the other, there muſt be three diſtinct perſons; the firſt is called the Father, the ſecond is called the ſon, the third is called the holy Ghoſt. This may be explained by two ſimilitudes. 1. is that of a body, which hath three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſions, longitude, latitude and profun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity, diſtinct one from the other, but not from the body. 2. is that ordinary example of our ſoul, which is but one being, though it hath three different manners of being: the firſt manner is to know, the ſecond is to wish, or wil, the third is to remember. Though theſe three manners or <hi>modes</hi> of being, are very different in themſelues, yet they are not things diſtinct from the ſoul. Q. But how can this be applyed to the Trinity?</p>
               <p>A. Thus. It muſt be granted that in the Deity we may conſider (and truly tis ſo) the Diuine nature, firſt, as hauing from it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf alone all knowledge, and all perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions. 2. this ſame Deity may be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as knowing or reflecting vpon its own knowledge, and perfections. 3. it may
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:184324:12"/>be conſidered, as infinitly louing itſelf and its infinit perfections. The Deity therfore or the Divine nature as it is the fountain of infinit fecundity, and the original prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, or giuer, is called the <hi>Father.</hi> The ſame Deity as it is conſidered not the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, but as if it were the riuer that flowes from that fountain, or the chanel that rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iues its own knowledge and perfections, is called the <hi>ſon;</hi> The ſame Deity as it is infinitly beloued by the Father and the ſon, is called the <hi>holy Ghoſt;</hi> which holy Ghoſt proceedeth as wel from the ſon as from the Father, becauſe each of thoſe two perſons equaly loue one an other, and the Deity: whence it followeth, that the Greekes error of the proceſſion of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt from the Father alone, and not from the ſon, is not only blaſphemy, but nonſenſe; becauſe it is impoſſible that ſuch a Father should not loue ſuch a ſon, and that ſuch a ſon should not loue his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they both hauing the ſame nature, and the ſame perfections. This is ſufficient of ſo ſublime a myſtery, the truth wherof though it can not be cleerly comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by ſo imperfect creatures as we are, yet our human reaſon may with ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability and proportion shew that the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:184324:13"/>vnity of the Diuine nature doth no more exclude the Trinity of perſons, than the vnity of a body doth exclude its three di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſions, or the vnity of the ſoul its three faculties.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>OF THE IMMORTALITY of the ſoul.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. Is the immortality of the ſoul an article of Chriſtian Religion?</p>
               <p>A. Yes, becauſe in the <hi>Creed</hi> we belieue the life euerlaſting.</p>
               <p>Q. May this article be proued by natural reaſon?</p>
               <p>A. yes, if you will admit there is any ſuch thing as reaſon in man. For, <hi>reaſon</hi> is that faculty wherby a man finds himſelf natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raly directed and inclined to raiſe his thoughts aboue and beyond the reach of his ſenſes; and to correct and contradict his own <hi>ſenſations,</hi> when he diſcouers that they are as falſe and fallacious as dayly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience doth manifeſt in familiar exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples v. g. of oares that ſeem to bend or break in the water; of ſophiſticated wine
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:184324:13"/>that ſeemes to be natural; of falſe colours; of mad dreames, and imaginations that in our ſleep or in a melancoly humor ſeem to be rational diſcourſes and real obiects; and other innumerable miſtakes, which are rectified either by reflexions of our own, or by the rules of perſpectiue phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy, and other ſciences, inuented by men to diſcern the difference that is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ween the true exiſtence, and the falſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of things.</p>
               <p>Q. How do you inferr that the ſoul is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, becauſe reaſon (which is the ſoul, or a faculty therof) doth direct and incline men to correct the fallacy of their <hi>ſenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and to raiſe their thoughts aboue, and carry them beyond the reach of our ſenſes?</p>
               <p>A. <hi>Senſation</hi> being a cooperation, or a ioynt operation of the body and ſoul, through the organization or miniſtery of our ſenſes, if the ſoul (or its faculty of reaſon) doth correct and contradict ſom of theſe ſenſations, and finds them to be falſe or fallacious, it is manifeſt that the ſoul may and ſometimes doth, operat not only independently of the body, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to thoſe appearances which ſeemd to be real, whilſt we were in it, and were
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:184324:14"/>directed by them, or belieued our ſenſes; and by conſequence the ſoul is immortal, becauſe the immortality of the ſoul is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but its independency of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by in acting and exiſting: and if it acts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our ſenſations when it is in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, queſtionleſs it may act without them, or independently of the help of the body; and if it can act independently of the help of the body, it may exiſt alſo without help of the ſame; and ſo the ſoul is proued to be immortal, or not to dye with the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, by its acting in the body, contrary to the <hi>dictamen,</hi> or appearence of our ſenſes.</p>
               <p>Q. Methinks this argument only proues that the ſoul may act (and by conſequence exiſt) independently of the body for ſom ryme, but proueth not that it may exiſt for euer independently of the body; and the immortality of the ſoul is not euery exiſten <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce, but an euerlaſting exiſtence indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of the boby.</p>
               <p>A. True it is that the immortality of the ſoul is an euerlaſting exiſtence without neceſſity of the bodyes help or ſupport; and as true it is, that reaſon, as ſoon as the ſoul knowes it ſelf, doth direct it to deſire and endeauour its own happineſs, which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:184324:14"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nuolues not only a perpetuity of exiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, but an euerlaſting felicity in the ſame exiſtence. That reaſons cleereſt act (after the ſoul knowes its own exiſtence) is, to direct and inſpire into the ſoul a deſire and endeauours of its own happineſs, is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt not only by that regret and remorſe of conſcience which men feel when they deuiat from the direction or dictamen of reaſon, but alſo by the loue which men bear to themſelues; which loue being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to be moſt euidently rational, can not but be directed by the cleereſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of reaſon. Vvherfore this deſire of the ſouls happineſs being directed by the clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt principle of reaſon, can not be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be a dreame, or deluſion, vnleſs you will maintain that the cleereſt reaſon is the greateſt folly, and by conſequence deſtroy the fundamental ground of all human diſcourſe and rational endeauours; If therfore the ſouls deſire of euerlaſting happineſs be grounded vpon ſo cleer a principle of reaſon, this (if it be not folly) muſt haue a real obiect wherunto we are directed, and wherwith we may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, without any poſſibility of miſtake; and if ſo, 'tis as demonſtrable that the ſoul is immortal, as it is that the moſt rational
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:184324:15"/>deſires and endeauours, are not manifeſt follies; and that the fundamental and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimental principles of reaſon can not be falſe, or fallacious.</p>
               <p>But if any one will be ſo mad as to grant that the firſt and fundamental principles of human reaſon are falſe and fallacious; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that herin he reflects vpon Gods wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, goodneſs, and gouernment, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſuch a ſuppoſition is not compati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, he muſt grant that there are ſom other contrary fundamental principles true, in oppoſition wherunto ours are falſe and fallacious. Let him therfore produce them, and maintain that it is reaſonable in lieu of honoring our parents, to hate them, in lieu of deſiring our happineſs, to wish our miſery, &amp;c. and if he can not produce any others beſides theſe, he can not think it reaſonnable we should credit theſe, or feare our ſelues can be miſled ſo long as we ſtick cloſe to our own principles of reaſon, and follow that light which shines, and euery man ſees in certain actions ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily and naturally aſſented vnto, and therfore common to all mankind.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:184324:15"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>OF THE VVORSHIP OF GOD, and the ſacrifice due to him.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. Seing you haue proued that there is a God, and that the ſoul is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, I would willingly know how God ought to be worshipt.</p>
               <p>A. God being the Author of all good,
<note place="margin">
                     <p>Mr Beacoz a learned Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, in his Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled the reli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ues of Rome, edit 1560. f. 344 ſaith, the Maſs vvas begotten, conceiued, and born anone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, if all be true that Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers vvrite.</p>
                     <p>Sebaſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in his Epiſtle for abr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gating all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non lavv, ſayth, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>diatly after the Apoſtles all things vvere tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nd vpſide dovvn, &amp;c. The Lords ſupper vvas tranſ formed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</p>
                     <p>Mr Aſcham in his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy for the Lords ſupper, p. 31. doth acknovv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that no begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge can be chevved.</p>
                     <p>The ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t rathers call the Maſs, the viſible ſacrifice, the true ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, the dayly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, the ſacrifice according to the order of Melchiſedech, the ſacrifice of the body and bloud of Chriſt, the ſacrifice of the Altar, the ſacrifice of the Church, and the ſacrifice of the nevv Teſtament.</p>
                     <p>See St Ignatius the Apoſtles Scholar in his Epiſtle to the Church of Smirna. St Irenaeus. l. 4. c. 32. of vvhom the Centuriſts ſay that he ſpeakes very in comodiouſly vvhen he ſayes that Chriſt tanght a nevv oblation, vvhich the Church receiuing from the Apoſtles, doth offer to God in all the vvorld. See Cent. c. 4. col. 63. and Cent. 2. cap. 10. col. 167. they affirm St Ignatius his vvords to bee dangerous, and <hi>quaſi errorum ſemina.</hi> See alſo Terrul ad ſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pul. cap. 2. Origen. in numer. hom 23. St Cyprian lib. 2. &amp; 3. verſ. fin. St Ambr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lib. 5. Ep. 33. <hi>Miſſam facere coepit,</hi> &amp;c. St Leo Ep. 81. ad Dioſcor. St Auguſt. term 91. de Temp. &amp; lib. 9. Confeſſ. cap. 12. &amp; in Enchird. cap. 110. &amp;c. Sayes that the Sacrifice of our price vvas offerd for his mother Monica, being dead; and that it is not to be doubted but that the ſouls of the dead are relieued vvhen for them is offered the ſacrifice of our Mediator, &amp;c.</p>
                  </note> the only beginning and cauſe of our exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence, the end and hopes of our happineſs, it is fit we exhibit vnto him the greateſt honor we can, not only euery one in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, by an inward ſubmiſſion of our ſouls acknowledging his infinit excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and our own nothing, and imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions; but alſo by an outward offering or oblation of ſom viſible thing that ought to be conſumed, or changed; therby to own Gods infinit power and Dominion ouer his creatures, and conſecrated to his Diuine maieſty by a ſolemn ceremony, and publik Miniſter. This way of worship is called a <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> and the publik Miniſter who offers it, is called a <hi>Prieſt.</hi> It hath bin practiſed ſince the beginning of the world, as appeareth in the ſacrifices of <hi>Abel, Noe,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:184324:16"/>Melchiſedech, Abraham, Iſaac, Iacob, Iob.</hi> and others in the law of nature, and in the written law of Moyſes, great part the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rof is nothing but rules and ceremonies concerning the manner of ſacrificing, and the habit and method which the Prieſt ought to obſerue in performing that pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blik miniſtery.</p>
               <p>Q. Vvhat is the ſacrifice of the Chriſtians, or of the law of grace?</p>
               <p>A. It is the ſacrifice of Chriſts body and bloud, offerd for the liuing and for the dead, vnder the <hi>ſpecies</hi> or appearence of bread and wine; and is commonly called the <hi>Maſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Q. Is not the ſacrifice of Chriſts body and bloud, as it was offerd vpon the Croſs, the proper ſacrifice of Chriſtians, or of the Catholik Church?</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:184324:16"/>
               <p>A. It is the moſt excellent ſacrifice that euer was offered; nay all other ſacrifices in the law of nature, of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> and of grace, did and do deriue their virtue and efficaciouſneſs from the ſacrifice of the Croſs; but becauſe Chriſt, as offered vpon the Croſs, is a general fountain of graces, and pardons, and the foundation of the ſacrifices of the old (as well as of the new) Teſtament, wherof they all were but ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, or figures, therfore that Diuine and bloudy ſacrifice of the Croſs can not be ſo peculiarly attributed to the law of grace, as to be called the proper ſacrifice of the Chriſtian and Catholik Church.</p>
               <p>Q. Is not the ſacrifice of the Croſs, and the ſacrifice of the Maſs, the ſame ſacrifice?</p>
               <p>A. They differ not in the ſubſtance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſame Chriſt is offerd in both, and Chriſt himſelf is the chief Prieſt in Both. But they differ in the manner, for in the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Maſs Chriſt is offered vnder the ſpecies or appearance of bread and wine, and in the Croſs he was offered in his own shape.</p>
               <p>Q. If the ſubſtance of the ſacrifice be the ſame, what need is there of that of the Maſs? is it not ſufficient that Chriſt offered himſelf vpon the Croſs once for all?</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:184324:17"/>
               <p>A. It is a general rule grounded vpon reaſon, and the concurrence or cuſtom of all Nations which euer profeſſed any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that euery particular Religion muſt haue its ſacrifice peculiar to itſelf; becauſe Religion being Diuine worship, and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice being an action profeſſing the Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of that which is worshipt, it inuolues a contradiction to ſay Religion, and no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, or to ſay, that a religion can conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, and the ſacrifice therof not continue. Seing therfore the Chriſtian and Catholik Religion doth continue, and that the blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſacrifice of the Croſs, or Chriſts paſſion, doth not continue, the ſacrifice of the Croſs can not be the proper and peculiar ſacrifice of the Chriſtian Religion, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholik Church.</p>
               <p>Q. It is not ſufficient that the effects of the ſacrifice of the Croſs continue in the Church though Chriſt ſuffered but once; for the cauſe may be ſayd to continue in its effects?</p>
               <p>A. It can not be properly ſayd that the cauſe continues in its effects. Otherwiſe it might be properly ſayd, that the Prieſtood and ſacrifice of <hi>Noe</hi> after the deluge (chap. 8. Gen) doth yet continue, becauſe the effect therof (viz. the aſſurance of not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:184324:17"/>ſuffering an other deluge) doth and will continue vntill the end of the world.</p>
               <p>Q. If all the ſins of the world be pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (or at leaſt be ſufficiently ſatisfied for) by the ſacrifice of the Croſs, what vſe is there for the ſacrifice of the Maſs? or how can it be a propitiatory ſacrifice, in vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue wherof ſins are pardon'd and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied for?</p>
               <p>A. It is not againſt the ſufficiency or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitneſs of the ſacrifice of the Croſs, that ſins be forguien, and ſatisfied for by the ſacrifice of the <hi>Maſs;</hi> not only becauſe the ſame Chriſt is offered in both ſacrifices, but becauſe the ſacrifice of the <hi>Maſs</hi> is a commemoration of that of the Croſs, and doth apply the ſufficiency of the ſame to the pardon of particular ſins, that were not committed before Chriſts paſſion, as we ſay of Baptiſm and other Sacraments. And if the ſacrifices of the old teſtament were propitiatory, in virtue of Chriſts paſſion, before he came to the world, there can be no ground to deny that the ſacrifice of the <hi>Maſs</hi> is a Propitiatory ſacrifice, in virtue of the ſame paſſion after that he ſufferd.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:184324:18"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>OF THE CHVRCH OF GOD, and of Diuine faith.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. Though I know that they who worship God as he commands, are his Church, yet there being ſo many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations of Chriſtians pretending them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues alone to be thoſe worshipers, and the true Church, or at leaſt a part therof, I would willingly know whether there be any certain and cleer ſignes wherby the true Church and its members may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned from all falſe and heretical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations? and what ſignes theſe are? I am ſatisfied that any two or more Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations diſſenting in any doctrin, can not conſtitute that Catholik Church, out of which there is no ſaluation; becauſe ſuch Congregations can not haue either vnity, or verity in that doctrin wherin they diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree; and by conſequence, ſeing God (who is truth itſelf and infinitly auers from falſood) can no more countenance, or confirm with ſupernatural ſigns the leaſt, than the greateſt falſood, that Church or Churches which propoſe contradictory
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:184324:18"/>Tenets (whether fundamental or not fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental) can no more be the Catholik or part therof, than God can forfeit his vera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, or incline and oblige men to belieue contradictory points, wherof one muſt needs be falſe.</p>
               <p>A. That there are certain and cleer ſignes wherby the true Catholik Church of God may be diſcerned from all falſe and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Congregations, is as euident as Gods veracity, and his inclination to truth; or as it is, that God did not inſtitute a Church wherin there could be no peace, concord, or order; but all muſt haue bin diſorder, confuſion and diſſention; For, if the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of euery of thoſe Congregations were as credible (by ſupernatural ſigns of their being the true Church) as they are confident in their pretentions of being ſo, the moſt learned and prudent men might liue and dye ſafely in the ſtate of perplexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and all the world (at beſt) muſt haue bin <hi>ſeekers,</hi> or <hi>ſceptiks;</hi> and there being no reaſon (in ſuch a caſe) to belieue, why rather one ſect than an other should be the true Church. Therfore God being the Author of truth, peace, order, and vnity, his Church can not be a Congregation of diſſenting, or perplexed people, changing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:184324:19"/>from one faith to an other, for want o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſcernable and ſupernatural ſignes, which none but the true Church ought to haue, to the end all men may find it out, and therby be directed to embrace the true Diuine worship and doctrin.</p>
               <p>Theſe ſignes muſt be ſupernatural; that is, ſignes, aboue the ſphere and power of natural cauſes; at leaſt they muſt ſeem ſo, not only to the vulgar people, but to the wiſeſt men and greateſt Doctors, after a diligent ſcrutiny, and mature conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all cauſes, and circumſtances: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they muſt be ſuch as produce in us an euident obligation of belieuing that God alone is the Author of the Doctrin propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as Diuine, and that he hath authoriſed that Church to propoſe the ſame. The ſigns muſt not only be obſeruable, but obuious to euery vulgar comprehenſion, and perceptible euen by our ſenſes. The reaſon is, becauſe many, of the myſteries which are to be belieued with Diuine faith, exceed human capacity, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as well the learned as the ignorant are to be inſtructed therin by the Church, and muſt take its teſtimony for a ſufficient proof of their obligation to belieue (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubting) that God reuealed thoſe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:184324:19"/>things which it propoſeth in his name, and they can not comprehend; though they be credibly reuealed. Now to belieue that things ſo difficult as many myſteries which the Church propoſeth, are true, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed by God; and that any man or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of men is authoriſed by his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine authority to propoſe and preſs ſuch things vpon our vnderſtandings, this belief I ſay, can not be a prudent or pious act, without ſeing ſeeiming ſupernatural ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnes, ſo obuious to all kind of people, that they may (if reflected vpon) exclude all prudent doubts of our being miſtaken, becauſe they muſt diſpoſe us to fix our thoughts ſo firmly vpon Gods goodneſs and veracity, that we aſſent with greater aſſurance to what the Church ſayes, and its ſignes shew, than if we had ſeen it; not becauſe the Church ſayes it, or becauſe the ſigns confirm its teſtimony, but becauſe we rationaly iudge it impoſſible, that God would permit ſuch an appearance and te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony to be falſly fathered vpon himſelf, or permit vs to be deceiued by ſigns ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kely to be ſupernatural.</p>
               <p>Q. How can a certainty only moral of God being the Author of the commiſſion and doctrin of the Church, be a ſolid and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:184324:20"/>ſufficient ground for acts of Chriſtian faith, wherby we belieue without the leaſt doubt, and by conſequence with more than moral certainty or aſſurance, that God is Author of the commiſſion and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trin of the Church? How can any pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent act of our vnderſtanding aſſent to more than it doth ſee? or aſſent with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter aſſurance, than there is appearance of the truth? An intellectual act or aſſent being an intellectual ſight of the truth of the obiect. To ſay therfore that by acts of faith we aſſent to more than we ſee, or with greater aſſurance then there is appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the truth, is as much as to ſay, that by acts of faith we ſee more than we ſee; and belieue more firmly than we can?</p>
               <p>A. The anſwer of this obiection is, that <hi>aſſent</hi> being no more than an interior yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a thing to be (as <hi>diſſent</hi> is an interior denying it to be) the aſſent of the mind is not alwayes an intellectual ſight of the truth of its obiect. It is not alwayes the ſame thing in the ſoul to ſay a thing is ſo, and to ſee it is ſo. For, if theſe two were the ſame, the ſoul could neuer aſſent or rely vpon authority, nor be miſtaken in any aſſent, becauſe it is neuer miſtaken in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:184324:20"/>its ſight of the truth. Beſides, this opinion that confounds the aſſent of faith with the ſight of the truth (whether it be in proper cauſes, or by its connexion with the eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Gods reuelation) takes away the obſcurity, liberty and merit of Chriſtian faith; becauſe à cleer ſight of the truth (by whatſoeuer means it coms) is not compatible with thoſe attributes. St Paul tells vs that faith is an argument of things <hi>not appearing;</hi> and ſurely if they do not appeare by faith, they are not ſeen by an act of faith. More. A great proportion of the ſupernaturality of faith and of its me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit conſiſts in ouer comming the difficulty we find not only in examining the moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and in adhering with the will, but in aſſenting with the vnderſtanding to the truth, and to the exiſtence of its reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; as, to that of the Trinity, Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp;c. But if our aſſent of faith were an intellectual ſight of the truth, or of the exiſtence of Diuine reuelation of thoſe my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, ſuch an aſſent could not inuolue, nor we find therin, any intellectual diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty: for, what intellectual difficulty can there be in ſaying inwardly, <hi>it is ſo,</hi> if we ſee it <hi>is ſo.</hi> There is rather a neceſſity (in ſuch a caſe) of ſaying, <hi>it is ſo.</hi> Faith is ſo
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:184324:21"/>far from being an intellectual ſight of the verities belieued or aſſented vnto, that the leſs cleerly you ſee the truth, or the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation credited (ſo it be prudently credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) the greater your faith is. Therfore Chriſt reproacht St Thomas for not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieuing the Reſurrection vntill he had ſeen with his eyes Chriſt reſuſcitated.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oan.</hi> 20.</note> And told him, they were happy that belieued, and did not ſee what they believed. Now the reaſon why faith and ſight or knowledge are ſo oppoſit, is; becauſe the nature and notion of faith is, to ſupply (and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence it doth ſuppoſe) the want of ſight or knowledge. Hence it is that many ſay faith and knowledge are no more conſiſtent one with the other, than the want and not want of the ſame thing. And indeed this notion of faith is well groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; becauſe experience doth conuince, and all confeſs, our human nature to be ſo imperfect, that it ſtands in need of Chriſtian faith to ſupply the want of kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wledge touching Diuine myſteries. And euen in worldly affairs we muſt in moſt rely (for want of cleerer knowledge) vpon the authority and teſtimony of law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full witneſſes, and take their word for legal euidence; which, as it is a ſufficient
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:184324:21"/>proof of what they teſtify, ſo is it a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the imperfection of our vnderſtandings; and that moſt of our hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man aſſents and iudicial ſentences are not intellectual ſights of the truth itſelf, but humble ſubmiſſions to the authority and knowledge of others which we belieue, though for ought we euidently know, we may be miſinformed by their miſtake or malice. But the ſupernatural ſignes of the Catholik Church do shine ſo cleerly vpon the ſame, that not any who reflects vpon them, and relyes vpon Gods veracity, can prudently entertain the leaſt feare or doubt of being miſtaken in its authority, or miſled by its doctrin, notwithſtanding that we do not cleerly ſee the Diuine truſt of the Church, or the infallible truth of its Tenets.</p>
               <p>But though the aſſent of Chriſtian faith be not an intellectuall ſight of the truth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed, or of the Diuine reuelation, it doth ſuppoſe (at leaſt in our Predeceſſors) ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, or an intellectual ſight of ſom ſeemingly ſupernatural ſigns, which being credibly reported to us by Tradition, are ſufficient to gain ſo much credit and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority for the Church wherin they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd, as that whoeuer doth not belieue
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:184324:22"/>its teſtimony, and aſſenteth or yeeldeth not to its doctrin as Diuine, is iuſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned by Chriſt himſelf in his laſt words to the Apoſtles;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Marc.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 16.</note> and therfore tells them that his Church shall haue viſible and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural ſignes, wherby it may be eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcerned from all heretical Aſſemblies, ſom wherof he ſpecified, as power to caſt out Deuills, to cure diſeaſes, to ſpeak vnknowen languages, to rid people of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents; Theſe, beſides others related in Scripture, as the Conuerſion of Nations to Chriſtianity, the continual ſucceſſion and ſanctity of Doctrin and Doctors, the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of profecy, and many ſuch miraculous marks, ioyned with profound humility, and eminent virtues, are ſo far aboue all heathens and heretiks pretended morality and ſanctity, that when their ſaints are compared with canonized Catholiks, they appeare to be but hypocritical ſycophants, puff'd vp with that ſecret pride, ſo proper to all ſectaries, preferring their own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uat interpretation of ſcripture before the publik ſenſe, and practiſe of a viſible and miraculous Church.</p>
               <p>Vve conclude therfore that an aſſent of Chriſtian faith is not an intellectuall ſight of the truth reuealed, nor of the reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:184324:22"/>and yet the faithfull do aſſent to both with no leſs aſſurance than if it had bin a cleer ſight of both; becauſe euery aſſent of Chriſtian faith is grounded vpon and directed by this truth, Gods goodneſs and veracity will neuer countenance falſood with miracles, nor permit errors in a Church, whoſe authority and teſtimony is confirmed with ſuch marks of his Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne miniſtery and fauor, as the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Roman Catholiks is. This shall be in the enſuing ſection more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly proued.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>SECT. VNICA. <hi>OF THE RESOLVTION, AND RVLE of Catholik faith, and vvhether this, or Hereſy, be conſiſtent vvith a cleer euidence of Gods revelation.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Q. Notwithſtanding you haue told me that the aſſent of faith is rather a ſubmiſſion or yeelding of our vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Diuine authority, than a ſight or euidence of the ſame authority or reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, yet other Roman Catholik Authors hold the contrary, becauſe they ſay that the tradition or teſtimony of the Church
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:184324:23"/>is the rule or motiue of Catholik Faith. Now this tradition affirming that the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deliuered to one an other from age to age, from yeare to yeare, the ſame doctrin in euery particular, which the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholiks now hold, and that they deliuered that doctrin not as the doctrin or opinions of men, but as the word and reuelation of God, it is as impoſſible we should not ſee this doctrin to haue bin reuealed by God, as it is, that a tradition ſo vniuerſal, wherin euery man was ſo particularly concerned, and which hath bin conueyed by ſuch euident ſenſations, (as that of <hi>hearing, preaching, ſeing, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> and <hi>profeſsing</hi> our faith by the moſt ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnificant words and actions) can be fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacious, or falſe, or that ſuch multitudes could forget, or would alter the doctrin of this year, which they had receiued as Diuine the yeare before.</p>
                  <p>A. I know that the Author <hi>of ſure footing</hi> hath writ with great zeal ſom Treatiſes vpon this ſubiect, and hath ſo confounded thoſe who aſſert only a moral certainty in <hi>Faith,</hi> that they can not vindicat them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from the Atheiſm wherunto their principles and bare probability of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity leads, and wherwith the aforeſaid
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:184324:23"/>Author doth vnanſwerably charge them. But becauſe he took or reuiued this way, thinking that by no other the certainty of Chriſtian faith can be made out, nor the <hi>Socinians</hi> argument (againſt the poſſibility of aſſenting by an act of faith with more aſſurance than appearance of the truth) anſwered; and that I belieue both theſe difficulties may, and ought to be ſolued otherwiſe, I make vſe of other principles for the reſolution and rule of faith.</p>
                  <p>Q. Vvhat is the reſolution of faith?</p>
                  <p>A. It is an orderly retrogradation from the aſſent or act of faith to its firſt motiue, or to that which moued, or made vs aſſent.</p>
                  <p>Q. Vvhat is the Rule of faith?</p>
                  <p>A. It is that which directs vs to that motiue, and to aſſent or belieue as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</p>
                  <p>Q. Is not the rule and the motiue of faith, the ſame thing?</p>
                  <p>A. Many confound the one with the other. But they are diferent things; The motiue of faith is Gods veracity. The rule of faith is the Teſtimony or Tradition of the Church. Faith doth not fallow the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of its rule; if it did, we could not call it a <hi>Diuine</hi> virtue, becauſe the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:184324:24"/>or Tradition of the Church (which is its rule) is <hi>human.</hi> Its called <hi>Diuine</hi> faith, becauſe it is <hi>ſpecified</hi> by, and relyes wholy vpon Gods veracity, and therfore is a Diuine virtue.</p>
                  <p>Q. Ought not the rule of faith be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible direction to the motiue of faith? Ought it not alſo be of ſuch a nature as to manifeſt cleerly its own infallibility to euery one that will examin the nature of <hi>Tradition,</hi> which is the rule of faith?</p>
                  <p>A. It ought to be an infallible direction in itſelf (otherwiſe it might lead vs out of the way) but that infallibility ought not be more manifeſt to vs than the infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of faith itſelf. The reaſon is, becauſe a <hi>Rule,</hi> as ſuch, is but a direction; and one may be infallibly directed though himſelf doth not Know it; as a ſeaman who obeyes the Pilot commanding him to ſteer his ship by ſuch and ſuch land marks. It is no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary part or property of a <hi>Rule,</hi> to eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence its own infallibility, unleſs the thing wherunto we are directed be <hi>ſelf euident</hi> and uiſible, as we ſee in the rules and inſtruments of Mecanik arts. But if the truth of that obiect or act wherunto a <hi>Rule</hi> directs us, be of its own nature obſcure, and not obuious to our ſenſes, but rather
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:184324:24"/>aboue the reach and ſight of our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, then the truth or infallibility of the Rule ought not to appeare cleerly to us; for, if it did, the <hi>Rule</hi> hauing a neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary connexion <hi>(a parte rei)</hi> with the act or obiect wherunto it directs, it would cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcouer to us the truth of that obiect or act, which is ſuppoſed to be obſcure. This is explained by examples. A man that is purblind, or trauells by night, may be ſafely and infallibly directed or led be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween precipices, or through an vncouth and vnknown path, though he doth not ſee his own ſafety, nor the skil of his Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, or the certainty of his way. Tis ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for his ſatisfaction, and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to beare patiently the incommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſneſs of his iourney, that being cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly informed he belieues his Guide is skilfull and honeſt. Tis ſo in our iourney to Heauen. Vve do belieue that the rule of our faith (which is Catholik <hi>Tradition</hi>) is infallible (by virtue of Gods particular aſſiſtance and protection) though we do not cleerly ſee or know it is ſo. Vve be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue alſo that euery aſſent of Chriſtian Faith is infallibly true though we can no more ſee its infallibility than we can the truth of its obiect, v. g. of the Trinity, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:184324:25"/>of Chriſt, Tranſubſtantiation, &amp;c. So that there ought not be greater or clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer euidence required for the infallibility of the rule of faith, than for the infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the truth of faith; this being the end, and the other but ſubſeruient to it. Tradition therfore (euen as it is ſealed with all the ſigns of the Church) doth not make cleerly euident to us that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed any article of faith, or any point of Chriſtianity, nay not that fundamental one of Chriſts Diuinity; for, though Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholik Tradition and the ſignes and mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the Church may make it cleerly euident to us that Chriſt reuealed our faith and doctrin, yet they do not make it cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly euident to us that Chriſt was God, or that God reuealed Chriſtianity: witneſs all the hereſies of witty and learned men in all ages againſt Chriſts Diuinity; and euery one Knowes that againſt cleer eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence their can be no hereſy.</p>
                  <p>Q. The Church being our Guide of faith, if ſom Doctors therof do not ſee cleerly the way, how can we be led to heauen? How can they induce heretiks to follow them, or aſſure them that the ſaying of our ſauior will not be verified in us, <hi>ſi caecus caecum ducat,</hi> or that our
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:184324:25"/>Doctors are not like the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies, <hi>caeci eſtis &amp; duces coecorum?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A. The greateſt blindneſs in faith is to pretend a cleer ſight of its rules infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. The Catholik Church (acording to St Paul and the Scriptures) is a Congregation of men who do not ſee what they belieue, and are led and directed by the holy Ghoſt in matters of doctrin. This Church is euery particular mans immediat Guide, becauſe we follow it, and hold faſt to its teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and tradition; but this Church alſo hath a Guide (the holy Spirit) which leads it (as Chriſt ſayes) <hi>into all truth</hi> by continualy directing it, and aſſiſting in its definitions and decrees. Vvhen the four firſt general Councells defin'd the Diuinity of Chriſt and of the holy Ghoſt, they did not cleerly ſee nor demonſtrat againſt heretiks the truth of that doctrin, or that God reuealed it. For if they had, the heretiks could not haue continued heretiks in their iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Its therfore fufficient that in the Catholik Church there be Doctors and arguments to demonſtrat that all Diſſenters or heretiks (by not ſubmitting to its doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trin and authority) go againſt reaſon, and the obligation all men haue to embrace that religion, which is moſt likely to be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:184324:26"/>Diuine, in regard of greater appearance therin of ſupernatural ſigns (which Chriſt ſayd his Church should haue) than in any other. To ground therfore the certainty of Chriſtian Faith, or of its rule, vpon any euidence which faith itſelf declares to be fallacious and fallible (as it doth declare the euidence of our ſenſes and ſenſations is in the article of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi>) is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy Chriſtianity; and therfore Tradition as receiuing its certainty from our ſenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, can not be a ſufficient ground for the certainty of Chriſtian faith.</p>
                  <p>Q. I pray reſolue your Catholik faith vnto its motiue.</p>
                  <p>A. That is don by anſwering queſtions, Thus. Vvhy do you belieue the myſtery of the Trinity, or Tranſubſtantiation? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God, who can not deceiue nor be deceiued, reuealed it. How do you know God reuealed it? If you ſpeake of cleer knowledge, I do not know that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed it. But if you will ſpeake properly as a Chriſtian, or as a man that vnderſtands what we mean by <hi>Faith,</hi> you muſt not ask how I know, but how, or why do I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue that God reuealed it? Then I will anſwer, that the teſtimony or tradition of the Church, confirmed with ſeemingly
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:184324:26"/>ſupernatural ſigns, teſtifying that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed thoſe myſteries, makes it euidently credible he did reueal them. But becauſe I know my vnderſtanding is ſo imperfect, that I can not pretend to infallibility, and my ſenſes are ſo fallacious, that by our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations we are often miſtaken, and that faith itſelf tells us ſo (in the article of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi>) I cant no aſſent to this article, or to the myſtery of the Trinity, or to any other (pretended to be euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reuealed by virtue of ſelf euident Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and infallible ſenſations) with that certainty which Chriſtianity requires, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till I reflect and rely altogether vpon Gods veracity, and apply it to the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid teſtimony and Tradition of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholik Church; which declares that itſelf is authoriſed by God (and shews for that authority ſeemingly ſupernatural ſigns) to propoſe as reuealed by him thoſe myſteries and all the other particulars of our Faith.</p>
                  <p>Vvhen I compare and apply the Diuine veracity to this teſtimony of the Church authoriſed by thoſe ſigns, I aſſent to all shee propoſeth as reuealed by God, by this act. <hi>Notvvithſtanding I do not ſee any cleer euidence or infallible connexion betvven
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:184324:27"/>the teſtimony or ſigns of the Church, and Gods reuealing its doctrin, yet becauſe Gods veracity and his auerſion from falſood is infinit, I do belieue as certainly as I do that God is infinitly inclined to truth, that he neuer did nor neuer vvill permit the leaſt falſood to be ſo authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticaly propoſed as his reuelation, or vvord, as I ſee euery point of the Roman Catholick doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trin is propoſed by the tradition and ſigns of that Church.</hi> This general aſſent is applyed to euery particular article. Heer you ſee that the motiue of our Chatholik Faith is not the Tradition or teſtimony of the Church, but only Gods veracity. You ſee alſo that the tradition of the Church is the rule of our Faith, becauſe it helps and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects vs to reflect and rely more vpon the motiue, which is <hi>Gods veracity,</hi> than upon Tradition itſelf. Laſtly you ſee there is no impoſſibility in aſſenting (by an act of faith) with more aſſurance than there is appearance or euidence of the truth aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto; becauſe the aſſurance is not ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from, nor grounded vpon the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, but vpon Gods veracity and his infinit inclination to truth. Hence fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth. 1. That whoſoeuer denyes any one article of <hi>Faith,</hi> (whether <hi>fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal,</hi> or not <hi>fundamental</hi>) belieueth none at
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:184324:27"/>all with Diuine or Chriſtian Faith; becau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe he ſlights the motiue therof (which is Gods infinit inclination to truth, and auer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from falſood) to that degree, as to be perſuaded the Diuinity can permit fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſood to be ſo credibly fatherd vpon itſelf, as the Roman Catholik Church doth its doctrin, with ſo ſeeming ſupernatural ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gns, and ſo conſtant a Tradition. The mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue of Faith being thus once ſlighted, none that ſo ſlights it, can belieue any thing for its ſake, or upon its ſcore. 2. It followeth, That the Tradition and Miracles of the Catholik Church do not make it cleerly euident to us that God reuealed any one article of Chriſtian Faith, nay not that fundamental one of the Diuinity of Chriſt. For, though <hi>Tradition</hi> makes it cleerly eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to us there was ſuch a man as Chriſt, and ſuch prodigies as his Miracles, and that him ſelf ſay'd he was God, yet that Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and thoſe prodigies do not make it cleerly euident to us, (as it did not to the Iewes) that Chriſt was realy God. For, if this had bin cleerly euidenc'd to them or us, neither Iewes nor Socinians or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ancient heretiks, could haue bin obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat or heretiks in their iudgments againſt Chriſts Diuinity.</p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:184324:28"/>
                  <p>Q. If I do not ſee an infallible conne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion between the aſſent or rule of Faith and Gods reuelation, I muſt needs ſee there is no infallible connexion, and may ſay, the aſſent of Faith may be falſe, ſeing <hi>Tradition,</hi> which is the rule of that aſſent, is fallible. On the other ſide I muſt ſayt he aſſent of Faith can not be falſe. So that if <hi>Tradition</hi> be not ſo ſelf euident as from it to conclude cleerly the impoſſibility of Faiths falſood, it muſt be granted that I ſee Faith is, and is not, infallible: and that <hi>Tradition</hi> is, and is not, an infallible Rule.</p>
                  <p>A. Though I do not ſee any infallible connexion between Gods reuelation and the Tradition of the Church, or any other rule directing to belieue what he realy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eueald, or (which is the ſame) between the aſſent of Faith, and the rule of Faith; yet it doth not follow that I muſt ſee, or ſay there is no neceſſary connexion between them. For at the ſame time I do not ſee that neceſſary connexion, or infallibility, I do belieue there is that connexion, though I ſee it not: nay tis therfore I can <hi>belieue</hi> it becauſe I do not ſee it: Faith requiring that what is belieued, be not ſeen. It would indeed be a contradiction to ſay, I ſee and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:184324:28"/>do not ſee the infallibility of <hi>Tradition,</hi> or of Faith; but tis not any to ſay, I do not ſee, and do belieue that infallibility. It may be as well ſayd a man who is blind, and infallibly or ſecurely led by a knowing Guide through a dangerous way, doth ſee his ruin or danger, becauſe he doth not ſee his own ſafety, or the infallibility of his Guide, though he belieues himſelf ſecure from all danger.</p>
                  <p>Q. Is it not cleerly euident that God can not permit falfood to be ſo authenticaly propoſed in his name, as the Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholik Church doth her doctrin, by ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued a tradition, and ſo ſurpriſing ſigns, as her miracles, ſanctity, conuerſion of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>A. Though I am of opinion God can not permit ſuch an appearance of Diuine truth to be a miſtake, yet our vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings being ſo imperfect, it would be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption in vs to define, or pretend to demonſtrat what God can do, or not do. Vve only know he can not ſin. But we do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ot know ſcientificaly whether he may not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to punish the ſins of ſome) permit the Church to err, and the world to be delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by their cleereſt and moſt frequent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enſations, wherupon (as our Aduerſary
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:184324:29"/>ſayeth) the certainty of Catholik <hi>Tradition</hi> is grounded. And though both Scripture and Tradition ſay, the Church shall neuer fail or err, yet we do not pretend to cleer euidence that either Scripture or Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is Gods word.</p>
                  <div type="subsection">
                     <head>SVBSECT. <hi>HOVV A MAN MAY ASSENT in matters of Faith, vvith more aſſurance than there is appearance of the truth.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Q. If it be not cleerly euident to us by the tradition of the Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholik Church, nor by Gods veracity, that he reuealed its doctrin, how can we aſſent or belieue with infallible certainty or aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, that God reuealed it? Is it in our power, or euen in Gods power, to make vs affirm inwardly and certainly any thing, we not knowing whether it be ſo, or no? How therfore can we affirm inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and certainly the truth of the Trinity, or that God reueald it, if we know it not cleerly either by Gods veracity, or by the tradition of the Church?</p>
                     <p>A. Aſſents grounded vpon authority differ in this from aſſents grounded vpon
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:184324:29"/>cleer knowledge, that the certainty of theſe are deriued from, and meaſured by the cleer ſight and euidence we haue of their truth, or of the obiects being as they are affirm'd to be. But the certainty of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents grounded vpon authority, is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued from, or meaſured by any cleer eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence or ſight of their truth, but by the perſuaſion we haue of the perſons we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue his knowledge and inclination to truth. Now all men who admit of a God, being moſt certainly perſuaded that he is infinitly inclined to truth, they may, and ought, to aſſent with the greateſt aſſuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce and certainty imaginable, that God did realy reueale all that which the Church propoſeth as Diuine doctrin; for, though wee do not ſee this truth in the myſtery or matter deliuered by Catholik tradition, nor in that euidence which our ſenſations giue to tradition itſelf; yet by reflecting vpon Gods infinit auerſion from falſood, and vpon our own perſuaſion of his infinit veracity, and ſeing ſo great an appearance of his being deeply engaged and concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for the truth of a Churches teſtimony that lookes ſo like his own, affirming the doctrin to be Diuine, we are bound in conſcience to belieue without the leaſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:184324:30"/>doubt, or at leaſt we are bound to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauor to belieue without doubt (which muſt be a rational endeauor ſeing our obligation of endeauoring is ſo euident to us) that God is the Author of the Roman Catholik doctrin, and hath reueald it; for, if he had not, he would neuer permit the ſame to be ſo plauſibly and probably propoſed as Diuine by Miracles and other ſigns of the Church, that prudent and learned men muſt ſin in being obſtinat againſt its doctrin and teſtimony. And this is that we mean when we ſay that we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the Diuine veracity to euery particular point of faith; not by ſeing the reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion itſelf in the tradition or teſtimony of the Church (for then we could not deny its doctrin was reueald, nor be heretiks) but by hauing ſo much veneration for Gods veracity, that whenſoeuer it ſeemes to be ſo publikly engaged, and prudently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieued as we ſee it is in the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lik Church, God ſpeakes, or reuealeth, what it propoſeth as his word.</p>
                     <p>Q. Methinks the veneration we haue for God and his veracity, ought rather oblige vs not to aſſent to any doctrin as ſpoken or reuealed by him, vnleſs it be cleerly euident to vs, that he ſpoke or
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:184324:30"/>reuealed it; for, if we do otherwiſe, we expoſe his holy name to contempt, and ourſelues to damnation: by uenturing to father what we fancy vpon God, when perhaps he neuer ſayd or reuealed what we imagined.</p>
                     <p>A. Its a prerogatiue due to ſoueraignty (and <hi>a fortiori</hi> to the Deity) to ſpeake and command by Miniſters and inferior offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, which beare the badges of the royal authority. And it is not only a diſreſpect, but obſtinacy and rebellion, not to obey lawes and commands ſo authenticaly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed. So likewiſe it muſt be not only a ſin of diſreſpect and contempt, but of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical obſtinacy, not to belieue that God ſpeakes or commands by the Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholik Church; when its teſtimony and tradition of hauing Gods truſt and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to declare that he ſpeakes or reueales its doctrin, is authenticaly propoſed by ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gns ſo ſupernatural in appearance that no human authority is ſo authentik, and no other Church can or dares pretend to the like. The more ſoueraign is any ſuperio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and veracity, the greater obligation there is in ſubiects not to exact for their obedience therunto, or belief therof, cleerer euidence of its commanding, than
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:184324:31"/>is uſual and ſufficient in human affairs when Princes proclaim or command. And the more infallible the veracity of him is who claimes the authority (if this be authenticaly propoſed) the greater is the obligation of aſſenting inwardly therunto, without cleerer euidence that it proceeds from the infallible Author of the ſame, than ſuch a moral certainty as the ſigns of the Church create: this being the cleereſt that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the nature, liberty, obſcurity and obſequiouſneſs of Chriſtian Faith.</p>
                     <p>Q. Ought there not to be in the true Church an euident and concluſiue argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt heretiks and Pagans, to let them ſee their obſtinacy, by shewing cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to them that God reuealed what they deny to be true, or to be matter of Faith?</p>
                     <p>A. If men were to be ſaued by Demon.ſtrations or cleer knowledges, deduced one from the other, what you ſay, were fit and neceſſary. But God hauing decreed to ſaue men by Faith, rather than by ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, by a meritorious and free, rather than a neceſſary or demonſtratiue aſſent of him ſelf being the Author and Reuealer of the Chriſtian doctrin, it is ſo far from being fit the Doctors of his Church should con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uict
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:184324:31"/>Pagans or heretiks by cleerly euiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing to them God reuealed the ſauing tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, that it is not poſſible. For, though ſom Diuines haue ſayd, Faith is conſiſtent with cleer euidence of God hauing reuealed the truth of its obiect, becauſe forſooth, though the belieuer doth ſee the truth (and by conſequence can not doubt of it, or be an heretik) yet he doth not ſee it in its proper cauſes, but only in Gods reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; notwithſtanding I ſay this vnwary opinion of ſom ſchoolmen, themſelues can not well reconcile with it the merit, obſcurity, liberty, and obſequiouſneſs of Chriſtian Faith, nor shew how 'tis poſſible for any learned Catholik or other man to be an heretik in his iudgment, becauſe the malice of <hi>Hereſy</hi> (this being an error in the underſtanding, as well as obſtinacy in the will) conſiſts in doubting or denying inwardly that God did reueal ſuch an arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Faith; but if euery learned Catholik doth ſee (by virtue of tradition) that he did realy reueal it, he can not ſee nor ſay the contrary in his mind, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence can not be an heretik. And yet its granted on all ſides that any learned man without forgetting any part of his learning or knowledge may be an heretik.</p>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:184324:32"/>
                     <p>Beſides, the aſſent and certainty of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Faith doth not enter further vpon its obiect than to ſay it exiſts, or that the act of Faith is true, it medles not with why it exiſts, or with any of its proper or particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar cauſes, that is, with any reaſons why the obiect exiſts, or why the act of Faith is true; it is grounded only vpon Gods re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation, and this ſayes no more than <hi>it is ſo,</hi> all other reaſons and cauſes are imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent, as to the nature and vſe of Faith; Faith being an imperfect knowledge and a total relying vpon the Diuine authority, and not vpon the knowledge of proper or any other cauſes. Now, it is impoſſible that the obſcurity and nature of Faith can be more (or ſo much) deſtroyd by ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent euidence, impertinent to its end and nature, than by an euidence that imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly and directly oppoſeth and is incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with its motiue, its merit, and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. If the act of Faith be not conſiſtent with the cleer ſight or euidence of its truth in the proper and particular cauſes, notwithſtanding thoſe cauſes are not its motiue, nor conſidered or toucht by the act, or aſſent of Faith; how can its merit, obſcurity, or nature conſiſt and continue with a cleer ſight of its truth, or of its
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:184324:32"/>motiue, or (which is the ſame) with eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Diuine reuelation? This ſight or euidence being as deſtructiue of the obſcurity and difficulty wee meet with in aſſenting to the myſteries and of the truſt we repoſe in God by belieuing (which is no leſs eſſential to Faith than its truth) as it is directly oppofit to the ſtate of obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity wherin we muſt be, if we truſt his word deliuered to vs by the Church, as alſo to the darkneſs and deſguiſe he muſt ſpeake to vs in, if he will haue vs truſt him and merit by Faith, or indeed belieue him at all; for, men do not belieue when they aſſent to a truth they ſee or can not deny. And it is impoſſible for them to ſee that God (who is truth itſelf) ſpeakes or reuealeth any myſtery, without ſeing alſo tis truth he ſpeakes or reueals. Our aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries ſeem to make the Montebanks ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>ſeing is belieuing,</hi> the rule of Diuine Faith.</p>
                     <p>Q. Vvhy should not the merit of Faith be conſiſtent with the cleer euidence of the truth therof in its proper cauſes; or with cleer euidence of Gods reuealing the myſtery belieued? Is it not ſufficient for a meritorious aſſent that the <hi>VVill</hi> applyed the vnderſtanding to cleer the difficulties
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:184324:33"/>which might retard or ſuſpend the act of Faith before its actual aſſent? Muſt this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent alſo meet with obſcurity, and ouercom a difficulty in ſaying (and not ſeing) that God reuealed what it aſſents vnto, after all our former pains taken in finding out the rule of Faith, and examining the nature of Catholik Tradition?</p>
                     <p>A. The chief merit of Chriſtian Faith con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in ouercomming the difficulty we find in aſſenting to more than we ſee, or with more aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce than wee ſee there is euiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of truth. If we did ſee, or certainly know that God reuealed what we aſſent vnto by the act of Faith, we could not haue that dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty in aſſenting to the myſteries therof which we find by experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: for, what diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty can there be in ſaying inwardly, God reuealed the Trinity, or the Trinity is true, if we ſee that God reuealed that myſtery, and (by an immediat conſequence) that it is true? Therfore the proper and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diat merit of an act of Faith (as ſuch) doth conſiſt in ouercoming the difficulty of actualy aſſenting that God reuealed the myſtery or matter we belieue he did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueale, though we ſee not his reuelation, nor any neceſſary connexion between it and the doctrin, tradition, or teſtimony of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:184324:33"/>the Church. As for thoſe other difficulties antecedent to this (and to the act of Faith) which we ouercom, and are rather diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions to make our ſelues fit to belieue (by remouing the obſtacles of education and cuſtom, or by examining the nature of <hi>Tradition,</hi> and the <hi>motiues of credibility</hi>) than immediat acts of Faith; the merit that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults from ouercoming thoſe difficulties, is not the proper and immediat merit of Faith itſelf, becauſe it is antecedent to it, for after all our aforeſaid inquiry and examination of the rule and motiues of Faith, we find ſtill a great difficulty in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting actualy or belieuing, that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed what <hi>Tradition</hi> affirms he did; this, our own experience doth demonſtrat, and it may be proued by diuers places of holy Scripture, as that of Luc. 19. when one hauing bin credibly informed (and perhaps ſeen) how Chriſt wrought many miracles, he deſired Chriſt to diſpoſſeſs his ſon of a dumb Deuil: Chriſt told him if he could belieue, he would deliuer his ſon from that ſpirit. Vvithout doubt the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther found great difficulty in the very act of Faith whereby he belieued Chriſts po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer; for though he ſayd, I do belieue, yet he cried out, adding, <hi>Lord help my incredulity.</hi>
                        <pb n="50" facs="tcp:184324:34"/>And yet this man was very well diſpoſed, and informed of Chriſts power and mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles before he brought his ſon to him, otherwiſe he would not have taken ſo much pains to follow him, and preſent his ſon before him.</p>
                     <p>And indeed <hi>incredulity</hi> (as obſtinacy alſo) doth ſuppoſe as much information and euidence of the motiues of credibility, and of the rule of Faith, or Tradition, as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſit for the actual aſſent of Faith; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe none could be called <hi>incredulous</hi> or <hi>obſtinat</hi> for not belieuing. The faithfull therfore merit and ouercom a great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty by the very act of Faith, after that all other difficulties precedent to it, are clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or ouercom. And in ouercoming this laſt great difficulty conſiſts chiefly the <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturality</hi> which is moſt peculiar to the act of Faith. Heretiks therfore may be conuicted of obſtinacy and hereſy, though they do not cleerly ſee, nor we euidently conclude (by tradition, or any thing elſe) that God reuealed what they deny or doubt of, and the Church propoſeth as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed by him: For, hereſy doth not conſiſt in an impoſſibility, but it would be one if it were requiſit that learned heretiks be obſtinat againſt a cleer and concluſiue
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:184324:34"/>euidence of God hauing reuealed what they deny or doubt of. How can any paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or pride blind a learned heretik (if it depriues him not wholy of his wits, and then he can not ſin, or be an heretik) ſo far, as to make him deny or doubt of what he ſees euidently concluded God ſayd, or reuealed? That were to deny God is God, or the exiſtence of a Deity. A learned here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tik therfore can not be better or more cleerly conuicted of heretical obſtinacy, than by our euidently concluding againſt him, that he is obliged in conſcience (to auoyd the threatned danger of damnation if he doth not belieue the Church, whoſe teſtimony is confirmed with Miracles) to aſſent to that doctrin as Diuine, which is deliuered by Catholik Tradition and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the motiues of credibility, though it be not cleerly euident that its doctrin is Diuine, or its tradition infallible. More of this hereafter. Now I will proue the euident obligation all men (who are informed of our Faith) haue to belieue the doctrin of the Roman Catholik Church as Diuine, as alſo how they are obliged in conſcience to inform themſelues ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:184324:35"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>HOVV THE MIRACLES OF THE Roman Church euidently conuict all its Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries of damnable obſtinacy; and hovv a credible report of them obligeth all men to inform themſelues of thoſe miracles, and doctrin confirmed by them; and that of all Chriſtian Congregations the Roman Catholik alone is the true Catholik Church.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. Suppoſing the Catholik Church can not be compoſed of all or any two Congregations diſſenting in the leaſt point of doctrin, as hath bin proued in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent Chapter, I deſire to know which of them all is that one true Catholik Church we ought to belieue, according to that article of the Apoſtles Creed <hi>I belieue in the holy Catholik Church,</hi> and out of which there is no ſaluation?</p>
               <p>A. You know the true Catholik Church is only that Congregation of Chriſtians which hath the ſigns Chriſt ſayd (Marc. 16.) should follow the true belieuers: and that thoſe ſignes are, the caſting out of Deuills (not by coniuring, but) in the name of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:184324:35"/>Chriſt; the gift of tongues, the conuerſion of Nations to Chriſtianity, the curing of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſes, raiſing of the dead, and other ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural marks of Gods truſt and truth committed only to the miniſtery of that Church, and by which marks i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> muſt be diſcerned from all falſe Congregations, pretending to be either the whole, or a part of the Catholik Church.</p>
               <p>Q. Out of your diſcourſe I gather that all the markes of the true Catholik Church are reduced to miracles; becauſe ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural ſanctity, the conuerſion of Nations to Chriſtianity, the gift of profecy, &amp;c. are as great miracles, as the caſting out of Deuills, curing diſeaſes, raiſing the dead, and the gift of tongues. But it is a common ſaying among Proteſtants, that miracles are ceaſed in the Church; and ſom Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liks grant they are ſo few, and wrought in thoſe remote regions of <hi>Iapan</hi> and <hi>China,</hi> that you can hardly meet with one who did euer ſee a miracle. How therfore can miracles be the marks wherby euery man may be directed to know the true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholik Church, if few or none ſee them?</p>
               <p>A. I grant that all the marks of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholik Church muſt be miraculous; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:184324:36"/>they were not fit motiues for pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent men to ſubmit their iudgments to the teſtimony or miniſtery of that Church, as to the Church of God. But miracles are not ceaſed, nor confind to thoſe remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te regions of <hi>Iapan</hi> and <hi>China:</hi> There is not a Catholik Nation in the world which doth not shew ſom things at leaſt ſo like ſupernatural miracles, that as wiſe and wary men as any in Chriſtendom, belieue them to be ſo. And ſuch Proteſtants as pretend they are not, can not with any probability shew that the matter of fact is falſe, or that the manner of working them is fraudulent or natural; ſeing therfore Chriſt himſelf aſſures vs that ſupernatural miracles shall follow the true belieuers, and that vntill the end of the world there will be true belieuers, and by conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce a Catholik Church, we are bound in conſcience to belieue, that only is the true Church, wherin we ſee (or at leaſt heare credibly reported) there are true miracles, or things ſo like true miracles, that as wiſe and as wary men as any in the world (after a ſeuere ſcrutiny, and ſerious ſtudy) miſtake them for true miracles, notwithſtanding they know that vpon their not being miſtaken in ſo important a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:184324:36"/>matter doth depend their euerlaſting hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, or miſery.
<note place="margin">Dr Dovvn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Treatiſe of Antichriſt l. 1. c. 9. pag. 111. ſaith, neither Turks, nor Ievves, nor any other Churches of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, but only the Pope and Church of Rome do vaunt of miracles.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Q. Is there but one Congregation of Chriſtians that pretends to ſuch miracles?</p>
               <p>A. No.</p>
               <p>Q. Vvhich is that?</p>
               <p>A. The Roman Catholik.</p>
               <p>Q. If all other Chriſtian Congregations be againſt the Roman Catholik, and that in euery Chriſtian Congregation there be as wiſe and wary men, and as willing to be ſaued, as any Roman Catholiks; why should any man be bound in conſcience to belieue the Roman Catholik miracles are true, when as great, or a greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of wiſe and learned men do maintain they are not true miracles?</p>
               <p>A. Vvhen learned parties agree in the fact of an accident ſo extraordinary, that no natural cauſe therof (after diligent ſcarch) can be knowen, but ſeemes to be aboue the power of all natural cauſes and human induſtry, doubtleſs the party which belieues the fact to be ſupernatural, or a miracle, deſerues to be credited before all which contradict the ſame, and can giue no good reaſon for their contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. 1. Becauſe in ſom Chriſtian Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation or other there muſt be true miracles,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:184324:37"/>otherwiſe Chriſts words, Marc. 16. can not be verified. And ſeing no other Chriſtian Congregation but the Roman Catholik pretends (at leaſt vpon ſo publik and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable grounds) to haue true miracles, the Roman Catholik is to be credited in this point before all others. 2. It is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with Gods infinit veracity to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſo publik and probable an appearance of true miracles for confirming falſood, as the appearance of miracles in the Roman Catholik Church is. For that, veracity is an inclination to truth, and an auerſion from falſood; and by conſequence, the Diuine veracity (being infinit) inuolues an infinit auerſion from falſood. But an infinit auer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from falſood is not conſiſtent with Gods permiſſion of ſo probable and plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible an appearance of true miracles to confirm any falſe doctrin, as we ſee in the Roman Catholik Church. Therfore if the miracles of the Roman Catholik Church be not true, Gods infinit veracity (as alſo his goodneſs and prouidence) may be queſtioned.</p>
               <p>This may be explained to the vulgar ſort by a ſimilitude. Suppoſe there were in ſom shire or town of England or Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land a company of men acting in the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:184324:37"/>Kings name, as his priuy or great Councell, with all the formes and formalities therof, as a Lord Chancellor, or Commiſſioner, Treſurer, Secretaries, members of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, Clerks, &amp;c. and that a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble part of the Nation obeyed their orders and commands, as men authoriſed by the King, who is not ignorant of theſe publik proceedings, and by conſequence can not be rationaly thought auerſe, but rather ſeem to approue of them, eſpecialy if he be able (without danger of diſturbance) to hinder and humble this pretended Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, by declaring them to be but a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Aſſembly of Cheats and Rebells, and by punishing them accordingly. A King I ſay that might hinder ſuch a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Parliament or Councell from abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing himſelf and his ſubiects by ſo ſeeming a legal authority, and yet would not, can not be thought to haue any truth, goodneſs, or iuſtice; becauſe by his conniuance at thoſe impoſtures, which he might haue diſcouerd without trouble or inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, he doth countenance, and confirm that Councell as commiſſioned by himſelf. This may be eaſily and aptly applied to the Roman Catholik Church, which is inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with ſo many miraculous marks of
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:184324:38"/>Gods authority, and therfore doth act by a warant ſo ſeemingly Diuine, that Gods bare permiſſion of ſuch a cheat as Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants ſuppoſe the Roman Catholik Church to be, would conclude his want of proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, goodneſs, and veracity, and by conſequence there can be no excuſe or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional hopes of ſaluation for Proteſtants, or any others that will not ſubmit their iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to a Church and doctrin ſo publikly commiſſioned and confirmed by Gods great ſeal, Miracles; as yet shall more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly appeare in the enſuing ſections.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I. <hi>VVHETHER THE CREDIBLE and conſtant report there is of true miracles vvrought in the Roman Catholik Church, be a ſufficient euidence to conuict of damnable obſtinacy and hereſy ſuch as ſtight them or vvill not heare of them.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Q. Is it then vpon this ground of not belieuing the Roman Catholik mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, which are recounted by the ancient Fathers or others, Roman Catholiks ſay, that we Proteſtants are obſtinat heretiks,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:184324:38"/>and that ſuch of vs as dye not members of your Church, are damned? Is not this a foolish and vncharitable opinion?</p>
                  <p>A. One of the grounds of that cenſure is the Definition of Hereſy, which is, <hi>an error in the underſtanding, and obſtinacy in the vvill againſt any truth or authority that is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficienly propoſed as Diuine.</hi> Now the great appearance and moral euidence there is of the Roman Catholik Church (together with its tradition) doth ſufficiently propoſe or declare its doctrine and authority to be Diuine. For, though it be not demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely euident that the Roman Catholik miracles are true miracles, nor that its tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition and teſtimony is infallible, yet it is moraly euident (and by conſequence ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently euident) that its doctrin is Diuine, and that God is Author of the ſame, it being confirmed by ſuch Miracles, and that by them he doth authoriſe that Church, as Princes do their officers by letters patents under their great ſeale; Miracles being the great ſeale wherwith Gods Miniſtery and doctrin is made authentik.</p>
                  <p>Q. Vvhat is moral euidence of a miracle!</p>
                  <p>A. Moral euidence of a miracle is, ſo credible and ſo conſtant a report therof, that to deny or doubt of the fact reported,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:184324:39"/>argues imprudence in the diſſenter, and renders his caution of not belieuing, both rash and ridiculous; becauſe it deſtroyes (at leaſt) all hiſtorical and human Faith.</p>
                  <p>Q. May not a man belieue Hiſtory, and rely vpon human authority, though he belieues not the ſtories of the moſt authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tik Roman Catholik miracles?</p>
                  <p>A. No, if he diſcourſeth conſequently, and according to the rules of reaſon, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of one principal is, that the ſame cauſe produceth the ſame effects; and the ſame authority the ſame aſſent or belief. If ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſame ancient Fathers or Authors vpon whoſe teſtimony or tradition you rely for belieuing a miracle of Chriſtian religion in genral, or of the Trinity or Incarnation in particular, recount the like miracles of Tranſubſtantiation, prayer to Saints, or Purgatory, you are rash and ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rational in contemning that ſame autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which you credited in as difficult a ſubiect, and as much aboue your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion: for, you ought to belieue both the miracles and myſteries, or nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  <p>Q. Is moral euidence of true miracles ſufficient to conuict of damnable obſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and hereſy all ſuch as ſlight that euiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:184324:39"/>and will not examin the grounds and effects therof?</p>
                  <p>A. Yes The reaſon is; 1. becauſe they are a ſufficient euidence that the doctrin confirmed by them is Diuine. 2. becauſe Chriſts miracles were only moraly (not demonſtratiuely) euident as miracles; for, if they had bin demonſtratiuely euident as ſuch, none of the Iewes could deny them to be Diuine, or could think they were wrought by the power of <hi>Beelzebub.</hi> And though it was but moraly euident that Chriſts miracles were true miracles, yet that moral euidence was ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uict the incredulous Iewes of damnable obſtinacy and hereſy.</p>
                  <p>Q. I deſire to Know what it is you call damnable obſtinacy?</p>
                  <p>A. Damnable obſtinacy is a ſetled reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of remaining in your own opinion of religion, or a neglect of inquiring into the grounds of any other, notwithſtanding the prudent doubts you haue, or would haue had (if you had not bin carleſs) of being ſaued in the way wherin you haue bin educated, or made choice of.</p>
                  <p>Q. I do agree with you that if one doubts of the truth of his own religion, he will be damnd unleſs he inquires into
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:184324:40"/>it, or ſom other, untill he doth what he can to be ſatisfied; but I can not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded that a man is bound to doubt of that religion wherin he hath bin bred, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he heares of miracles wrought in an other, unleſs his own be ſo abſurd, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſequent, that he muſt doubt of its truth whether he will or no.</p>
                  <p>A. There are two ſorts of doubts. 1. is a doubt which occurrs to ourſelues by our own obſervation. 2. is a doubt not ſtarted by ourſelues, but by ſom other more lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in matters of religion, and as much to be credited, and as litle to be ſuſpected of hauing any deſign (but our ſaluation) in our change of opinion, as he whom we moſt confide in. Doubts of our own ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation are very ordinary, being groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the moſt obuious occurrences, as a publik change of Religion, either vpon the ſcore of conſcience, or intereſt: this laſt is as ſuſpicious (euen to the dulleſt comprehenſions) as the other is edifying. Not only the change into a thriuing reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, but conſtancy in a perſecuted one, doth make great impreſſion vpon all ſorts of people, as alſo relations of miracles cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly reported. Theſe impreſſions, and the inſpirations which follow them, raiſe
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:184324:40"/>doubts; and theſe) if not endeuored to be cleered) are a ſufficient cauſe of damnation.</p>
                  <p>The doubts which are raiſed in ourſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lues by the example, or the diſcourſe of others, who haue no deſign vpon us but the ſaluation of our ſouls, are alſo damnable to us, if we neglect the cleering of them by all the wayes that a buiſneſs of ſo great importance doth require. And the more diligent we muſt be in the ſearch, by how much more the perſons intereſted in main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining our perſuaſion (I mean ſuch as liue by the miniſtery therof) deterr us from ſo rational a ſcrutiny; which they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer diſſuade us from, if they did not feare a diſcouery of their own wickedneſs, and of their cauſes weakneſs.</p>
                  <p>Q. I pray ſir, apply this diſcourſe to the Proteſtants, and Roman Catholiks of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland.</p>
                  <p>A. I beg your pardon ſir, I am loath to offend the Parliament. But I will apply it to the Arians and Roman Catholiks of Spain. The Heir of that Croun, Prince <hi>Hermenegild,</hi> hauing bin bred an Arian, doubted of the truth of that pretended reformation; this doubt was ocaſioned by the diſcourſe he had with St <hi>Leander</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of <hi>Seuil.</hi> At length he was conuinc't
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:184324:41"/>of the falſood of that Arian hereſy, and reconciled to the Roman Catholik Church. The King his Father would needs haue him receiue the Arian communion, which the Prince refuſing to do, the wicked Father (for fear of his people) ſacrified the Heir apparent of the Croun to their fury, and cauſed him to be murthered. This change to, and conſtancy in the Roman Catholik Religion (together with a report of ſom miracles) wrought ſo much upon all the people of Spain, that a litle after, they all turned Catholiks; and a law was made, that none but Catholiks should haue em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment in that Kingdom. Hence you may inferr what ſtrong influence the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of a religious and reſolute Prince hath euen vpon the moſt uulgar iudgments, and how damnable it is in all people, not to examin the motiues of ſo edifying a conuerſion as that wherby one hazards and waues the greateſt temporal intereſt; and how certain it is that God will punish as well in this world as in the next, all ſuch as reſiſt or neglect the impreſſions and inſpirations which men feel in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to follow a religion ſo generouſly profeſſed, and preferrd before all the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and glory of an Imperial Croun.</p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:184324:41"/>
                  <p>Q. If Princely ſuffering vpon the ſcore of conſcience be ſo great a miracle, why shall not the Lady <hi>Iane Grayes</hi> ſuffering (and Queen Elizabeths alſo) for the Proteſtant religion, be miracles; and confirm that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion as the true Catholik? Add to theſe the patience and conſtancy of thoſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Proteſtant Martyrs recounted by Iohn Fox in his Acts and Monuments.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II. <hi>OF THE DIFFERENCE BETVVEEN Catholik conſtancy, and heretical obſtinacy: and vvherin doth each conſiſt.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Your obiection is material, and I shal endeuor to anſwer it as cleerly and in as few words as I can: but depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of a proper <hi>notion</hi> of hereſy, it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolues ſom difficulty. Experience and hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory hath proued (almoſt in euery age) that ſom heretiks ſuffer with as great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution all Kind of torments (and death itſelf) for their falſe religion, as Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liks do for the true one. And yet we all agree in terming the heretiks reſolution, <hi>obſtinacy,</hi> and the Catholiks <hi>conſtancy.</hi> The
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:184324:42"/>reaſon is, becauſe the heretik ſuffers for adhering to a particular opinion, and to his own priuat iudgment; The Catholik for conforming himſelf to the belief of the uniuerſal Church, and for ſubmitting his iudgement to the ſame. Therfore St Paul ſayes that an heretik is condemned by his own proper iudgment;
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Petr.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>No pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecy of Scripture is made by priuat interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi>
                     </note> and St Peter tells us that the true interpretation of Scriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re is not that of a priuat man, but of the Church. And the very word <hi>Hereſy,</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies a particular choyce, or a wilfull di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſion and declining from the firſt doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trin.</p>
                  <p>This ſuppoſed, there can be no diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty in declaring why an heretik may without any miracle ſuffer with great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution the greateſt torments for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining his hereſy; Becauſe men are natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inclined to follow their own opinions, and to maintain their own choice, and therfore we ſee what endeuors are uſed in vain, to perſuade an humorſom and wilfull man or woman, to recall any foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Act they did of their own heads; and how hard it is to conuince them that it was ill don. Now, euery heretik makes his religion his own act, not by an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſubmiſſion of his iudgment to the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:184324:42"/>Church (as Catholiks do) but by a proud preference of his own vnderſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that of all others. This needs no other proof than that pitty which euery pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Proteſtant (euen the women) hath of the moſt learned Roman Catholiks ignorance and Idolatry. In this pride and preference of their proper iudgment, and in the wilfulneſs of continuing in their own choice, doth conſiſt the obſtinacy of heretiks; as the conſtancy of Catholiks takes its denomination from that reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious perſeuerance which is grounded vpon ſo rational a reſolution as it is to ſubmit and ſtick to the doctrin of a Church ſignaliſed with ſo many ſupernatural and uiſible marks of being truſted by God, to teach and preach the true Catholik Faith, as hath bin demonſtrated in the 5. Chap.</p>
                  <p>Q. I grant that the difference between Catholik conſtancy and heretical obſtinacy is, that this is a more wilfull than rational adherency to a mans proper opinion, or to a priuat interpretation, of Scripture againſt the teſtimony and tradition of the Church; and Catholik conſtancy is a religious perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerance in a reſolution of ſubmitting our iudgments to the ſame Church: but how will you make it appeare that our Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:184324:43"/>interpretation of Scripture is a priuat one or that we are guilty of pride, ſeing we follow the interpretation of the Church of England, and ſubmit our iudgments therunto?</p>
                  <p>A. I will make that heretical obſtinacy appeare in thoſe very Proteſtant Saints and Martyrs which <hi>Iohn Fox</hi> doth celebrat for their conſtancy. And to begin (as you do) with the moſt innocent of them all, the Lady <hi>Iane Grey,</hi> shee did wilfully chooſe, and preferr before the Catholik, a new religion, or an interpretation of Scripture that was not as old as herſelf, though she was very yong. It had bin hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cht by <hi>Cranmer,</hi> and confirmed by the Parliament of Ed. 6. but ſome fiue years before she ſuffered: and was then Known and declared by an other Parliament (1. Mar.) to be hereſy, and contrary to the publik ſenſe and continual tradition of the Catholik Church, and therfore was called by the Proteſtants themſelues a <hi>Reformation of the old doctrin.</hi> So that though the Church and Parliament of England in the reign of K. Ed. 6. called it à <hi>Common prayer,</hi> or a publik worship, yet was it declared by the Parliament of Q. Mary a bundel of <hi>Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> errers, and priuat opinions, which
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:184324:43"/>himſelf and ſom few others inuented, or borrowed from <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Caluin,</hi> and other Innouators, who had reſolued to make themſelues popular and powerfull by ſetting vp their own priuat interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Scripture, and opinions for points of Religion. So that though all England, or a greater part of the world than En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland is, should embrace that Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſubmit their iudgments to that Church, their proteſtant Tenets are ſtill priuat opinions, and the ſubmiſſion of their iudgments to the ſame doth ſtill inuolue that pride and preference of their own choice of a nouelty, or new interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Scripture before the ancient doe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trin and againſt the publik teſtimony of all precedent English Parliaments, as alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the tradition of the Catholik Church. As for Queen Elizabeth, shee accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated her religion to the times, untill shee got the Croun; and then shee made uſe of the new Faith to ſerue her turn, and ſecure her intereſt. Indeed <hi>Iohn Fox</hi> his Martyrs were great but foolish ſufferers; their ignorance was proportion'd to their ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy; they caſt themſelues into the fire without Knowing wherfore. And yet Iohn Fox ſayes thoſe Tinkers, Tanners,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:184324:44"/>and ſilly women confuted the Bishops that endeuored to ſaue their liues, which them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues had forfeited acording to the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient lawes of the land. And though they dyed not Martyrs, yet they dyed like En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glishmen, that is, with as litle concern and as great courage, as if their cauſe had bin better. But this is no miracle in England, though the foolish partiality of <hi>Iohn Fox</hi> his pen doth endeuor to make his Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Readers miſtake thoſe proud mad fellows for pious Martyrs.</p>
                  <p>Q. Though I do approue of your diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between heretical obſtinacy, and Catholik conſtancy, yet I muſt ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn your application therof to prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy and popery, for an other reaſon; which is, that Proteſtancy is ſo far from inuoluing pride, that the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland doth not as much as pretend to be infallible in its doctrin; neither doth it exact from its children a ſubmiſſion of their iudgments to itſelf, but only to Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. And I hope there is as much humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity (I am ſure there is more ſafety) in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting our iudgments to Gods written word, as to the tradition of the Roma Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholik Church.</p>
                  <p>A. As I commend the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glands
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:184324:44"/>modeſty and ingenuity in acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging its fallibility, and in diſpenſing with the ſubmiſſion of your iudgments to the ſame (no fallible Church can exact or expect a ſubmiſſion of iudgment in any points of doctrin) ſo muſt I continue in my opinion of the pride and obſtinacy of proteſtancy. 1. Becauſe you will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue any thing inculcated to you by God, vnleſs it be deliuered to you in writing, as if the Diuine maieſty had not as much right to command by orders intimated to us by word of mouth, as by his writing. All the true belieuers of the world vntill <hi>Moyſes</hi> his law, were gouernd by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony and tradition of the Church, wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thout any writing or Scriptures: neither is any thing written in the old or new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament wherupon Proteſtants may with any color of probability ground their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended priuilege of not belieuing any thing but Scripture; and this doth in many places tell them, they are as much obliged to belieue Tradition, or Gods unwritten word, as the written. Now, why English<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and ſom Northen people alone, should refuſe to obey the Catholik Church, vnleſs it shewes for euery particular Gods order in writing, is not intelligible, them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:184324:45"/>and all other Nations owning the contrary to be prudently practiſed in all human gouernments? This muſt be pride and obſtinacy.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The pride and obſtinacy of this their pretended priuilege (which is the life and fundation of all Proteſtant <hi>Reformations</hi>) is further diſcouered by the practiſe of aprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple wherin all Proteſtants agree: which is, that not one of them thinks he is bound in conſcience to ſubmit his iudgment to any of their own or any other Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſenſe of Scripture in controuerted texts, if that ſenſe agreeth not with his own priuat interpretation; If that of his Church agree not with his own ſenſe, he may ſtick to his own, and reiect the other. And this is the reaſon why Proteſtants are diuided into ſo many ſects. How this prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple and practiſe may be excuſed from heretical pride and obſtinacy, I know not: For, they ſtand at a defiance with all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and will as litle ſubmit their iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to their own, as to that of <hi>Rome.</hi> Euery Proteſtant is by the fundamental <hi>Tenet</hi> of the Reformation his own Maſter, and a ſupreme Iudge of Gods written law. Doth not this demonſtrat how thoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations are founded vpon pride and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:184324:45"/>obſtinacy? Can there be greater, than that ſimple men and ſilly women should preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to be Maſters and Iudges of thoſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine and incomprehenſible myſteries? That they should preferr their priuat iudgments before that of their own Church, and of ours, vnto which the greateſt Doctors in all ages haue ſubmitted? Vvhat a proud, foolish, inſolent, and obſtinat people would the English conclude any other to be, wherof not one would acquieſce in the iudgment or ſentence of the Courts of <hi>Iudicature,</hi> but euery one aſſume to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the power of deciding his own law ſuites, and of appealing from the <hi>Chancery,</hi> or euen from the Parliament, to his own priuat opinion and iudgment? Let euery Proteſtant know this is his own caſe in matters of religion. He appeals in what concerns Faith and the ſenſe of Scripture, from his own Church and the Catholik, and general Councells, to his own proper iudgment. Doth he think that Chriſt would inſtitute ſo abſurd a ſpiritual gouernment? Can any man of ſenſe imagin it agrees with Scripture? To what purpoſe then should the Scriptures and St Paul bid us be of one belief, peaceable, and humble? Is any of theſe virtues, or that of Catholik Faith,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:184324:46"/>conſiſtent with ſuch pride, obſtinacy, and diſſentions, as this principle muſt inſpire, and we ſee in all the reformed Churches, and in that of our own Countrey? You ſee therfore that your reformed Churches and interpretations of Scripture haue ſo litle in them of the vnity, obſequiouſneſs, and humility of Chriſtian Faith ſo much recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to us by St Paul, that they ſeeme to the moſt learned Roman Catholiks not only to ſauor of hereſy, but to be the very ſource of heretical pride, and damnable obſtinacy, ſo far are they from hauing the leaſt ſmack of the fundation or fruit of Chriſtianity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III. <hi>SOM INFERENCES FIT TO BE conſidered by all Proteſtants, and vvhether any may be ſaued if they dye in that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IF Proteſtancy doth inuolue that pride and obſtinacy which I haue endeuored to proue, and deduce from its principles, without doubt he who dyes a Proteſtant, is damn'd. But Becauſe ſom are called
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:184324:46"/>
                     <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and yet know not what <hi>prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy</hi> is, I will deliuer my opinion how far their ignorance may excuſe them from being damnd by their profeſſion.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. No Proteſtant Bishop or Miniſter can be ſaued, if they repent not their hauing bin of that religion. The reaſon is; though many of them were more ignorant than they are, yet that ignorance can not excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe them, becauſe their calling doth oblige them to be at leaſt ſo learned in Hiſtory (if not in Diuinity) as to know the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelty of their own reformed Tenets, and the manners and motiues of the Authors of their Reformations. Theſe hauing bin ſo contrary to Chriſtianity and morality, the Preachers and Promoters deſerue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo well as damnation, either for damning others, or for not knowing they will be damn'd themſelues.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. No man or woman that hath read, or heard the contents of Doctor <hi>Heylins</hi> Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Church of England, or of any ſuch Proteſtant Author, relating the change of Religion, and the cauſes of that change in our Countrey, can be ſaued, if they continue and dye Proteſtants. For, the cheat of that change is ſo viſible, the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues ſo wicked, and the practiſes of the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:184324:47"/>Authors and Actors ſo abominable, that there is not the leaſt room left for a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable excuſe, or conſcientious miſtake. The ſpiritual ſupremacy of a layman doth not only inuolue a contradiction, but the occaſion of King Henry 8. aſſuming it, was ſo ſcandalous, and the way of exerciſing it ſo ridiculous, that euery one was as much offended at his preſumption in making himſelf Chriſts Vicar <hi>in ſpiritualibus,</hi> as they were at his profaneſs in making <hi>Cromuel</hi> of <hi>Putney</hi> his own Vicar general ouer the Clergy. And all this confuſion was raiſed, becauſe the Pope would not comply with his luſt in diuorcing him from his lawfull wife, and marrying him to <hi>An Bullen.</hi> There was not a man in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland then, who did not ſee and ſay from whence the Kings ſpiritual ſupremacy (the fundation and diſtinction of prelatik Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtancy) had its riſe, and their ſaying is to this day continued, and growen a rude Prouerb.</p>
                  <p>As for the change of the <hi>Maſs</hi> into the <hi>Common prayer,</hi> it ſeemed euen to all the poor Countrey folks ſo abſurd, that they took up arms againſt it in K. Ed. 6. reign: and both it and the whole prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Reformation was condemned as
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:184324:47"/>hereſy by Act of Parliament, 1. Mar. And though the ſame Reformation was again reſtored by an other Act of Q. Eliz. ſom fiue years after, yet euery one Knew that the very ſame perſons who voted for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring it were they who had condemn'd it, and now went againſt their conſcience for Q. Elizabeths ſake, who not only pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed rewards, but gaue hopes (as Doctor <hi>Heylin</hi> Confeſſeth) of marrying herſelf to diuers perſons (euen of the lower Houſe) vvho vvere inſtrumental in getting Votes, and ſecuring her intereſt by reuiuing and ſetling that Religion vvhich themſelues had cryed dovvn as hereſy in Q. Maries dayes. Vvhat ploughman or Ditcher in any part of England hath not vvit and learning enough to confute and contemn ſuch a change, and ſuch a reformation? There needs no Logik or Diuinity. A bare Knovvledge of the fact is ſufficient to diſcouer the fraud. Fevv in England are ſo ignorant as not to Knovv that Henry 8. turnd avvay Q. <hi>Katherin</hi> for his loue to <hi>An Bullen,</hi> and that Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> brought in the nevv Religion to ſtrengthen her vveake title to the Croun againſt the Knovvn right of the <hi>Steuards.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Though it vvere granted that the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:184324:48"/>Knowledge of this change of Religion doth not quite conuince the moſt illiterat and dull people of its falſood, yet it can not be denyed but that it muſt of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity raiſe prudent doubts againſt its being Diuinely inſpired; and that whoſoeuer is careleſs in cleering thoſe doubts, doth ſin mortaly, and will be damn'd, if he dyes in that ſin. For, a prudent doubt is as if it were the twilight of reaſon, diſcouering ſom abſurdity in that which formerly we unwarily belieued, not reflecting upon the ſame untill ſom new chance, or circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance made it appear more cleerly unto us. Vvhen this new chance or circumſtance doth make an impreſſion upon our mind and conſcience, we are bound to inquire after the cauſe and cure of that impreſſion and remorſe; if not, the ſore will turn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a canker, which can not be otherwiſe preuented than by a conſcientious curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, according to euery ones capacity. The illiterat perſon is not bound to learn to read, or to ſtudy Philoſophy, but he is bound to repair to his honeſt neighbors, to inquire and hear what the Papiſts can ſay for their Religion, as well as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants. And if he doth this without preiudice, and with a good intention,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:184324:48"/>he will cleer his doubt and conſcience.</p>
                  <p>Q. I am confident there are many poor Countrey fellows in England who neuer heard of King Henry 8. <hi>amours</hi> with <hi>An Bullen,</hi> nor of his aſſuming the ſpiritual ſupremacy, nor of Q. Elizabeths reuiuing proteſtancy to ſalue her own illegitimacy, or to ſecure her intereſt againſt the Queen of Scots right. How then can theſe men doubt or diſcourſe of what they neuer heard? muſt they alſo be damn'd?</p>
                  <p>A. There is not one in England who hath not heard of <hi>Perſecution</hi> and <hi>Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> againſt Papiſts, and that theſe men ſuffer for their conſcience, and the old Religion. This can not but excite a curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity to Know what men theſe are, and why they should be ſo foolish, as to ſuffer for ſo ridiculous a Religion, and ſo ſtrange a Beaſt as the <hi>Parſon</hi> deſcribeth both the Pope and Popery to be, when he forgets his ſermon, or hath a mind to diuert his Audience, or incenſe them againſt Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liks. By theſe and other ſuch wayes the moſt dull men com to heare, and may be informed, of the Roman Catholik Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions antiquity, as of the nouelty of the Proteſtant, and how this came to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced; this once Knowen, all the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:184324:49"/>induſtry and artifices of the Proteſtant par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will neuer be able to preuent, or root out of mens minds thoſe rational doubts which are grounded vpon the light of common ſenſe, when it diſcouers (as it muſt in this caſe) the leaſt deformity or diſſonancy againſt reaſon in any obiect whatſoeuer. For, what can be more diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the very firſt principles of reaſon, than to preferr a priuat new and intereſted ſenſe of Scripture before that old one which the Church ſtuck to as authentik for ſo many ages? The English Bible or Tranſlation, before that which all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom hath bin ſay'd by aboue 1200. years? An Act of Parliament of Queen Elizabeth and the Abettors of her intereſt, before all other Acts of English Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and all general Councells? The authority of ſuch debaucht Friers and Prieſts as <hi>Luther, Caluin,</hi> and the firſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Reformers, before that of all the holy Doctors and the whole body of the Roman viſible Church ſince the Apoſtles? In a word, new fancies called a <hi>Reformation,</hi> before that old Chriſtianity wherin our Anceſtors, as alſo our Kings, liued and dyed ſo happily? and wherin (as the learned Proteſtants themſelues confeſs) they were
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:184324:49"/>ſaued; wheras we all deny that they can be ſaued by Proteſtancy.</p>
                  <p>Q. I ſee you are of opinion that no Proteſtant at all can be ſaued. Vvhat? Can none of them haue inuincible ignorance? Is there ſo cleer and obuious an euidence of the Roman Catholik being the true Church, that none can pretend nor plead ignorance of that truth?</p>
                  <p>A. That out of the true Church there is no ſaluation, is a maxim of Faith wherin the holy Fathers agree. That the ſame Church is ſo viſible and preferable before all others, that euen the moſt ſtupid may as eaſily ſee it, as a Citty vpon a mountain, and therfore are commanded to repair to it, is manifeſt in Scripture. That the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholik hath thoſe cleer marks of Gods fauor, which perſuade the moſt ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous it is the true Church of God, hath bin in the 4. Chapter demonſtrated by us, and appeareth by thoſe ſupernatural ſigns of miracles, ſanctity, conuerſion of Nations to Chriſtianity, &amp;c. which shine in it, and haue ſet it out ſo gloriouſly in all ages and places of the world ſince the preaching of the Apoſtles. That in England there is any corner or perſon wherin common ſenſe can be ſo burried, or curioſity ſo
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:184324:50"/>dead, as to be ignorant of theſe things, and others deliuered by tradition from age to age, and year to year, is not credible. But in caſe there be any Proteſtant ſo neer a beaſt as not to reflect vpon any thing he ſees or heareth of his own or of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; his Baptiſme will ſaue him, if he did not looſe, by a mortal ſin the grace which he receiued in and by that Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And this is all the comfort I can giue my Proteſtant friends, whoſe ſaluation I more heartily wish, than thoſe do, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude them with larger opinions.</p>
                  <p>Q. This is but very cold comfort. Vvill not God grant to ſom poor ignorant Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant <hi>an act of contrition,</hi> at leaſt in the laſt hour?</p>
                  <p>A. I think not. But if he doth to any, it is to ſom of thoſe ſtupid Creatures I laſt ſpoke of. As for others, who haue wit and wayes to conſider and reflect vpon thoſe doubts which occurr to themſelues, or are raiſed in them by the diſcourſe of others, their obſtinacy or affected igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in not liſtening, or inquiring into a matter ſo important, and ſo eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued, makes them incapable of ſo great a fauor as an act of contrition. And as for thoſe erneſt or <hi>bigot</hi> Proteſtants, they are in
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:184324:50"/>greateſt danger of any, and furtheſt from contrition; becauſe hauing a cleerer Kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wledge of their own religion, and ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding much time in the meditation therof, they muſt needs haue great doubts, if they do not ſtifle them in their firſt birth, by diuerting their thoughts to more pleaſing obiects, and by auoyding all occaſions of diſcourſing of proteſtancy, as commonly they do, eſpecialy when they perceiue there is any likelihood of laying open the weakneſs of its principles, and the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs of the firſt Reformers. Beſides, an act of <hi>contrition</hi> inuolues Faith, hope, and charity, and theſe Proteſtants not hauing Faith, but rather an auerſion againſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of it, are not in a diſpoſition fit for contrition, which is the greateſt grace God doth to his moſt eminent ſeruants, and the Saints of his own Church.</p>
                  <p>Q. Methinks this is very hard. I can not as yet comprehend why a deuout Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant may not be capable of an act of contrition. Is proteſtancy ſo abominable in the ſight of God, that he will not turn his mercifull eye towards Proteſtants? Is it wors than other great ſins which God doth pardon? Is it hereſy? And if it be, may not an heretik haue an act of contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:184324:51"/>Is the malice of hereſy ſo great as to exclude Gods mercy?</p>
                  <p>A. Vvithout doubt <hi>Hereſy</hi> is the greateſt of ſins, and yet excludes not Gods mercy; but an Heretiks conuerſion precedes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, this not being compatible vvith hereſy. I vvill briefly tell you vvherin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts the malice of hereſy, and leaue your<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to iudge vvhether proteſtancy be He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy. The malice of Hereſy conſiſts in the contempt of Gods veracity. And Gods ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racity conſiſts in an infinit inclination to truth. An infinit inclination to truth is not conſiſtent vvith a permiſſion of falſood credibly fathered and faſtned upon him that permits it, if he can eaſily hinder the ſame. Now, the malice of hereſy conſiſts in hauing ſo mean an opinion of Gods veracity, or of his inclination to truth, that he vvould permit a Church ſo credibly pretending to be his own, as the Roman Catholik doth (by its miracles, its ſanctity its conuerſion of Nations to Chriſtianity, and other ſupernatural marks) to impoſe upon the vvorld (in his name) for ſo many ages, falſe doctrin for true; vvheras it vvas in his power euery moment of all that time to diſcouer and declare the cheat, and diſown the doctrin. And yet he did
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:184324:51"/>not either. That our miracles father our doctrin upon God, is eaſily proued; for, though the firſt Proteſtant Reformers and their ſucceſſors cry out againſt ſom of our miracles as falſe, yet they are forc't to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs ſom of them are true; and vve joyn with them in cenſuring falſe miracles as ſuch, and punish them who feign them as Malefactors. Againſt our conuerſion of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to Chriſtianity (a confeſſed mark of the true Church) they haue nothing to ſay; and as litle againſt the ſucceſſion and ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of our Doctrin and Doctors. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this credible (and indeed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincing) appearance of our miracles, and of the Roman Catholik Church being the true one, commiſſioned by God to inſtruct his people, yet the Proteſtants will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue it, nor ſubmit their iudgments to ſo authentik an authority, nor hearken to the Diuine voice manifeſting itſelf by the clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt ſigns and euidence that is conſiſtent with the freedom, merit, and obſcurity of Chriſtian Faith. Vvhether this obſtinacy be not hereſy, let the Proteſtants them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues iudge; and examin whether to ſlight the teſtimony and ſigns of ſuch a Church, be not a contempt of Gods veracity, as ſuppoſing he can permit falſood to be ſo
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:184324:52"/>plauſibly fatherd upon him as wee ſee the Roman Catholik doctrin hath bin for ſo many ages, and throughout all parts of the world.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>OF THE MINISTERY OF THE Church, and of the nullity of that of England.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AS it is neceſſary that Gods Church should haue viſible ſigns wherby it may be diſcerned from all heretical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, ſo it is acknowledged that in the ſame there is a Miniſtery caracteriſed with ſuch publik ceremonies and authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tik teſtimonies, that there can be no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of counterfeiting a miſſion or voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo ſacred. In the Chriſtian Church the Miniſters are called Bishops and Prieſts. Both are conſecrated by a real impoſition of Epiſcopal hands, and other ceremonies which haue bin practiſed in the Church euer ſince the Apoſtles, from whom by a continual ſucceſſion the Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal caracter muſt deſcend, and be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; otherwiſe no credit is to be giuen
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:184324:52"/>to any perſons claiming to be Bishops of whoſe ordination Prieſtood depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth.</p>
               <p>It was the misfortune of the Proteſtant Reformations, that the Authors therof were not Bishops, and, by conſequence, could not tranſmit either that caracter, or that of Prieſtood to their ſucceſſors, as they did their doctrin. This defect they endeuored to ſupply by perſuading ſuch as belieued them, that no <hi>indelible</hi> carac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or <hi>viſible</hi> ceremony of impoſition of Epiſcopal hands, was neceſſary for a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Ghoſpel. And euen the Church of England was neceſſitaded to approue of this deſperat doctrin (in the 25. of its 39. articles of Religion) becauſe it was then well Knowen, the Conſecrators of her firſt Bishops were no real Bishops, though they were called ſo for reaſon of ſtate. One is, that the conſtitution of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Parliaments requiring Bishops as one of the three eſtates of the Kingdom, and their votes being a conſiderable addition to the ſoueraigns authority, of which alone their nomination dependeth, Q. Elizabeth in this particular of Epiſcopacy went againſt the principles of other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations, and would needs Keep vp the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:184324:53"/>name of Bishops in her Church. But it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened very croſs to her deſign, that none of the Catholik Bishops of England (no others were then there liuing) would lay hands upon, or conſecrate any of thoſe new ones which she named to that digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>See the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſsion and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation in Doctor Bramhall the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hop of Derry, his vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland. See the ſtatut.</hi> 8. <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1.</note> Therfore she was forc't to iſſue forth a ſecond commiſſion for that purpoſe and therin to diſpenſe (by virtue of her ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſpiritual iuriſdiction) <hi>vvith the very ſtate and condition of the Conſecrators.</hi> And this power and practiſe hauing bin publik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excepted againſt (by Catholik Authors in print) as null, and ridiculous, it was confirmed and declared by Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (8. Eliz. 1.) that whatſoeuer had bin don untill then in making of Bishops, Archbishops, &amp;c. by the Queens commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion under the great ſeal of England, should ſtand as ualid, whether the Conſecrators were Bishops or no Bishops; any <hi>perſon or perſons vvhatſoeuer,</hi> hauing bin declared capable of giuing that caracter to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, prouided they were authoriſed ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by her Maieſties commiſſion under the great ſeal.</p>
               <p>This occaſioned great diſputes between Doctor <hi>Haiding</hi> and Doctor <hi>Iuel,</hi> one of the firſt Proteſtant Bishops. Doctor <hi>Haiding</hi>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:184324:53"/>in his printed bookes deſired M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Iuel</hi> to name the Bishop that conſecrated him, <hi>Parker,</hi> and the reſt of Queen Elizabeths firſt Bishops; and was content to ſubmit to <hi>Iuel,</hi> and own the validity of his and the other proteſtant Bishops conſecration, if he would name <hi>Parkers</hi> Conſecrator. A man would think this was no ſuch intricat matter, nor ſtrong argument, if euer <hi>Parker</hi> had bin conſecrated by a Bishop. And yet <hi>Iuel</hi> hauing bin thus prouoked by his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting Aduerſary, could neuer name <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi> Conſecrator, of whoſe conſecration depended that of the reſt; nor produce Regiſters of that conſecration, when <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> called for them, though ſom 50. years after, appear'd in print a very formal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter of <hi>Parkers</hi> conſecration, copied for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth out of Records Kept in Lauander at Lambeth. The unſeaſonable appearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of this new found Regiſter occaſioned much laughter, and new diſputes which haue continued vntill theſe times. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it can not well enter into any conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering mens heads, that <hi>Parker, Iuel,</hi> and the firſt proteſtant Bishops (who were called by Catholiks <hi>no Bishops</hi> in print, for want of a right Conſecrater, and challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to name the Bishops that conſecrated
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:184324:54"/>them or <hi>Parker,</hi> their aduerſaries ſetting their ſtreſs vpon that only argument) would not take the pains to ſee and ſearch their Regiſters of Lambeth for a Bishops name that imported them ſo much to na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, if any ſuch Bishop had euer bin, or any ſuch Records had bin then extant. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, ſure their memories were not ſo short, as not to remember without the help of Regiſters and Records the name of a man that their Succeſſors pretended (fifty years after the time of anſwering was paſt) had made <hi>Parker</hi> a Bishop but fiue years before they were askt the queſtion, with ſo much ceremony and ſolemnity. For, <hi>Hardings</hi> book and Iuells anſwer were printed an. 1565. or therabouts.</p>
               <p>An other thing made the prelatik Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies caracter abſolutly null. And that was the <hi>Form</hi> which they uſed in the conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their Bishops and Prieſts. This <hi>Form</hi> was iudged eſſentialy defectiue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe not one word therof did expreſs or mention the caracter pretended to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen therby. And though the Church of England for neer one hundred years had defended and practiſed this <hi>Form,</hi> yet at length they were forc't to ſubmit to their Aduerſaries exceptions and reaſons againſt
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:184324:54"/>it, and to change and correct the Form, as wee directed in the bookes we writ againſt the ſame. Vpon the Kings reſtaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they printed their <hi>Ritual</hi> and therin you may ſee the words <hi>Bishop</hi> and <hi>Prieſt</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto the Form of their conſecrations, which (or their equiualent) are abſolutly neceſſary; and yet nothing like them was in the old Forms, and former editions. This humility of theirs is to be commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, though it be to no purpoſe, ſeing the change made not them who went before it, Bishops; and though their late refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Form be valid, yet when pronounced by men that are not Bishops, it works no effect, nor giues any caracter either of Prieſtood or Epiſcopacy to themſelues or their Succeſſors. And none of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Clergy hath bin conſecrated by a true Bishop ſince the change of their old Form.</p>
               <p>Let the Proteſtant Layty now reflect vpon the caracter and conſcience of their Clergy, as being men who take vpon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the adminiſtration of Sacraments, abſolution from ſins, ſpiritual juriſdiction, and all functions belonging to true Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops and Prieſts; though themſelues can not but know there is no probable ground
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:184324:55"/>to belieue they are ſuch. I ſay nothing of the reuenues they are poſſeſſed of vpon the account of being Churchmen; but I can not be ſo uncharitable as not to aduertiſe my Countreymen of the danger they are in, and of the damnation which will follow, if by timely repentance and a generous re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution they do not withdraw themſelues from the direction of ſuch Teachers, and from the Miniſtery of ſuch a Clergy. Vvhat can they anſwer to the, obiection we bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row from the ſtatut 8. Eliz. Can they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin that the Queen would diſpenſe with the <hi>ſtate</hi> and <hi>condition</hi> of the Conſecraters, if they had had the Epiſcopal caracter? Vvhat need was there of a diſpenſation with their <hi>ſtate</hi> and <hi>condition,</hi> if they were real Bishops? Vvhy should the Parlament con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm this diſpenſation, and enact by law, that whatſoeuer was don by this commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Queens, should be valid, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Conſecraters were Bishops or not; the words are, <hi>by any perſon, or perſons vvhatſoeuer.</hi> All that my Countreymen can ſay, is, that they haue an Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the caracter of their Clergy, and for the ſaluation of their ſouls. Vvhat that will auail them in the other world, I wish they did conſider. Surely they can not but
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:184324:55"/>know that ſuch Acts, will be no excuſe before that dreadfull Iudge, who takes no other euidence but that of our own conſcience. This only we muſt conſult in matters of Eternity, and not think that a Clergy or Religion eſtablished by a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral law, is lawfull, though it should be called legal by an Act of Parlament.</p>
               <p>Q. Sir, I haue ſeen the Regiſters of <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> you would haue me ſuſpect as forged. I aſſure you I ſee no ſign of forgery in them. And as for Bishop <hi>Iuels</hi> not anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Doctor <hi>Harding</hi> demand, concerning the firſt Proteſtant Bishops (and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly <hi>Parkers</hi>) Conſecrator, perhaps he thought it an idle queſtion, and underua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lued ſo weak an obiection.</p>
               <p>A. Forged Regiſters are often the moſt formal, all counterfeit ware ſtanding in need of being ſet forth with great artifice. Vve haue ſeen Regiſters and Records of publik Courts of Iudicature ſo artificialy changed and corrupted, that nothing but their not being produced many years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, when they were called for, could conclude the forgery. Doctor <hi>Harding</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for the Regiſters of the firſt proteſtant Bishops Conſecration, as well as for the Conſecraters name: Neither did B. <hi>Iuel</hi>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:184324:56"/>contemn this demand, as you imagin. He went as far in the anſwer as he durſt. He anſwered, 1. that the firſt proteſtant Bishops in the beginning of Queen Elizabeths rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gn, were conſecrated in due form by Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chbishop <hi>Parker</hi> their Metropolitan: But being again preſſed by <hi>Harding</hi> to name <hi>Parkers</hi> Conſecrator, he put off that imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent queſtion (wherof the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſy and the credit of the Church of England depended) by a wild digreſſion and long diſcourſe of the ancient Bishops being conſecrated without aquainting the Pope. But ſure M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>Iuel</hi> might aquaint Doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>Harding</hi> with the name of him who conſecrated <hi>Parker,</hi> as well as he named <hi>Parker</hi> for Conſecrator of the other Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hops; and certainly would, if <hi>Parker</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had bin realy conſecrated by a Bishop. If you do not belieue my relation, read Doctor <hi>Hargings</hi> bookes againſt <hi>Iuel,</hi> and <hi>Iuels</hi> own Apology for the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, where they treat of this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular.</p>
               <p>Q. Gentlemen, I would to God you did agree among yourſelues, and not break the Layties heads with your diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. You haue put ſo many doubts into mine, that I can hardly belieue any thing.
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:184324:56"/>On both ſides you ſeem to bee honeſt and learned men; therfore I think my beſt way is, to continue in the Church of England, and truſt in God, that I shall not be dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n'd for not being of that of Rome, untill I be better ſatisfied that the points wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it differs from ours are neceſſary for ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. And this requiring longer time, (the particulars being ſo many) than I am like to liue, t'is not credible God would oblige me, or any other illiterat perſon, to ſpend our dayes rather in controuerſies than in prayer and good works; and in the end be as litle ſatisfied with ourſelues as our and your Clergy are with one an other. Yourſelues grant that implicit Faith is ſufficient for ſuch ignorant people as I am, that Faith, I am ſure I haue; for I do belieue all that God reuealed, though I do not know what it is he reuealed, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he hath apointed the Church of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, rather than that of England, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the world, and inform us of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelations. And truly I belieue a man may be ſaued without troubling himſelf to know which of them it is that God hath apointed for our inſtruction, prouided we be redy to be members therof when that shall be made cleer to us by better
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:184324:57"/>arguments than I am able to inquire after.</p>
               <p>A. This is ſo dangerous doctrin, that I iudge it worth my pains to shew yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the obligation the moſt illiterat men haue to ſearch after the true Church, and how eaſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y they may find it out by viſible ſigns; and how you may without any help, but that of common ſenſe, be ſatisfied of the truth of euery particular point of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trin wherin Roman Catholiks differ from Proteſtants: And all this in the ſpace of leſs than two houres time.</p>
               <p>Q. Nay Sir, if you perform your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, I deſerue to be damn'd for all Eeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, if I will nor hear you for ſo short a time as two hours. I pray Sir proceed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>HOVV EVERY ILLITERAT PERSON may eaſily and in the ſpace of two houres, find out the true Church, and the truth of euery point of doctrin controuerted betvveen Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholiks and Proteſtants.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHen the people of Iſrael were moſt diuided in matters of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<note place="margin">3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 8.</note> the Prophet <hi>Elias</hi> made a motion to
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:184324:57"/>them of cleering the truth by that famous <hi>dogmatical</hi> Miracle of burning an Ox upon the Altar without kindling the fire under it. This cleer and compendious way was hugely approued of by the multitude, as ſuting beſt with their capacities, for, they needed not learning to diſpute, their eyes were ſufficient Iudges, and they had ſo much common ſenſe as to know, that God would not permit a falſood to be confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>md by a miracle in ſo publik a trial, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Veracity was ſo particularly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned. The Prophets therfore of <hi>Baal</hi> durſt not refuſe ſo fair an offer as <hi>Elias</hi> made in their preſence, and I hope the Proteſtant Clergy will be ashamed to refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe mine. Let us not delude the people with ſchool ſubtilities, or obſcure texts of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. If the Church of England or Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land or any other reformed one be the true Church, and its doctrin the true doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trin, let that be tried by miracles. I shall try ours of Rome by that teſt. I challenge then all the Bishops and Miniſters of the Church of England and all others of the Reformation, or all the Proteſtants of the world, to work, or mention any one mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle euer yet wrought by any Proteſtant to confirm any one point of doctrin
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:184324:58"/>wherin they differ from the Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholik. Gentlemen, ſummon your Sinods, ſearch into all hiſtories, profane, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred, ſet your heads together, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce at leaſt ſom probable teſtimony of as much as one miracle to grace your Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations. And if you can not find undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted miracles, at leaſt shew ſom thing that lookes like a miracle; ſom thing that may be miſtaken for one, wherof the falſood or fraud hath not bin as yet diſcoured: ſuch as you ſay many of ours are. Perhaps you will pretend that your Proteſtants are not ſo eaſily foold with falſe miracles, as our Roman Catholiks. But this muſt be a gift and priuilege of your priuat ſpirit; for, the Spaniards, Italians, and French, are not by nature ſo dull as our Northen Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and are as loath to be cheated out of their moneys by Maſſes, Miracles, Pilgrimages, and other pretexts of deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as you are. And yet they belieue ſuch Miracles, as haue bin motiues for the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, or people, to <hi>Canonize</hi> our Saints, and thoſe alſo wherby Heathens and heretiks haue bin conuerted to our Religion.</p>
               <p>Q. I doubt not Sir, but that the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liks are as unlikely and loath to be impoſed vpon, as Proteſtants; therfore I would
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:184324:58"/>fain heare ſom of thoſe undeniable mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles you pretend to haue in your Church, and for confirmation of the doctrin wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in you differ from us. But I pray let them be Miracles like thoſe of Chriſt, for I will not belieue any others. I giue you this cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for feare you should trouble me with Mother <hi>Iulianas</hi> fits, and one <hi>Finaghtyes</hi> triks, wherwith he deluded the common people heer in England and Ireland, where that mans Miracles (as I heare) are mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cryed up.</p>
               <p>A. Sir, you haue reaſon to expect I should relate unto you Miracles like thoſe of Chriſt, ſeing himſelf hath ſayd (Iohn. 14.22.)
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luther to</hi> 7. <hi>l. de Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeis. &amp;c. fol.</hi> 210. <hi>A Deo didi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimus, &amp; accepimꝰ, aeternum verbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; veritatem Dei hacte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus mille quingentio annis mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculis &amp; ſignis con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſam &amp; confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>he that belieueth in me, the vvorks that I do, he shall do, and greater.</hi> Vvhich words not only Luther the firſt Proteſtant Reformer, but your English Bibles (edit. 1576.) in the marginal notes, referr <hi>to the vvhole body of the Church, in vvhom this virtue doth shine for euer.</hi> Though I muſt confeſs, both Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and our English Proteſtant writers contradict themſelues again in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar (as all men muſt who maintain errors) and ſay, when we preſs them to relate ſom of their Miracles, that Miracles are now ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous, and therfore none wrought in the Church. But I shall deal ſo impartialy
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:184324:59"/>with Proteſtants in this matter, that I will not mention any miracle for confirmation of the Roman Catholik Church and doctrin, which the beſt Proteſtant writers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues do not confeſs to be miracles, though others of them attribute the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king therof to the power of <hi>Beelzebub</hi> (as the obſtinat Iewes did of Chriſts) and that, for no other reaſon but becauſe the mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles were wrought by Papiſts, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm Popery.</p>
               <p>As for <hi>Finaghtyes</hi> miracles, I made it my buiſneſs to inquire after them, and him alſo; and do find, that ſo ſoon as he began to work his miracles, the Popish Archbis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hop of <hi>Tuam</hi> in Ireland (who was his <hi>Ordinary</hi>) queſtioned him for that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, and finding him both ignorant and obſtinat, he forbid him the further tempting of God, and ſcandalizing the Church by his foolish attempts. But the mans zeal or vanity preuailing more vpon his Spirit, than his Superiors commands, he continued his ridiculous courſe, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon was commanded out of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishops Prouince. After that vigilant Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lats death, <hi>Finaghty</hi> lurking for ſom time in other places, came into England, and from thence returned to <hi>Dublin,</hi> where he playd
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:184324:59"/>the fool with breathing, and beating the Deuil in good erneſt; one <hi>Stanton</hi> (an other mad Prieſt of his Countrey) printed many of his rash attempts for great miracles. <hi>Finaghty,</hi> after that his manner of exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſms had hin examind, and found to be different from thoſe of the Church, and his diſpoſſeſſing of Deuils to be without any viſible marke or ſign of the Deuils poſſeſſion, or at leaſt departure, was ſilenc't by the Clergy of Dublin, and commanded out of that Province. From thence he went to his own <hi>(Conaght)</hi> and falling again to his old miracles, he was by the Popish Bis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hop of <hi>Elfin</hi> depriued of his general Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carship, and that extraordinary reſpect for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got which the ſimplicity of the people had offered to his ſuppoſed ſanctity; by vvhom now he is much ſlighted. My cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity inclineth me to belieue, that his grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt fault was folly, and that he was more cheated by the Deuil, than ſo ſimple a man could deſign to cheat others. I haue bin more diffuſe upon this ſubiect than you may think it deſerues, becauſe the world may be ſatisfied None ſuſpects the truth of miracles, nor corrects the foolish Pretenders of working them more, than we Roman Catholiks; it being one of the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:184324:60"/>greateſt cares of our Bishops and Paſtors, to preuent ſuch impoſtures, and to punish the Impoſtors, And this hath bin the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual practiſe of our Church, euer ſince the beginning of Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p>Q. You haue giuen me great ſatisfac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by your relation and opinion of <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naghty,</hi> and his miracles. If they had not bin ſo ſoon, and ſeſonably condemn'd by his own party, I should ſuſpect that all your other miracles reported in Legends and Saints liues, were of the ſame natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. But now I ſee that miracles which were neuer contradicted or ſuſpected by yourſelues are credible. I pray therfore relate thoſe, which you ſay are confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or allowed of by the learned Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, and yet confirm your doctrin in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to theirs.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:184324:60"/>
                  <head>SECT. I. <hi>THE CONVERSION OF THE Heathen Kings and Nations from Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm to Chriſtianity, and Popery, is an euident miracle and mark of the truth of the Roman Catholik Church and doctrin, in oppoſition to that of all Proteſtant Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">Its continuance euen from the Apoſtles to this preſent demonſtrated, as alſo the impoſsibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of its pretended inſenſible change.</head>
                  <p>THe greateſt of all miracles (it being the end for which they haue bin wrought, and the Chriſtian Church inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted) is the conuerſion of the Heathen Kings and Nations to Chriſtianity. If ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it be proued, that all the Heathen Kings and Nations which haue bin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted from Paganiſm to Chriſtianity, we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re conuerted to no other but to that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity which Proteſtants call <hi>Popery,</hi> and that the ſayd conuerſions were perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by knowen Papiſts, and confeſſed miracles, our Aduerſaries muſt acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that the Roman Catholik Church,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:184324:61"/>(and it alone) is the true Church of God; otherwiſe it will follow, that Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted his Church to no purpoſe; and that his deſign and deſire of the conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Nations, and ſauing their ſouls, came to nothing. Nay it will follow, that Chriſt is not the <hi>Meſsias,</hi> to vvhoſe doctrin and Church (as the Scriptures and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets foretell) <hi>all Nations shall flovv, and their Kings Miniſter, the multitude of the ſeas shall be conuerted, the Iles shall vvayt for, and the Heathens be its inheritance, and the end of the earth its poſſeſsion.</hi> All this the Proteſtants themſelues confeſs to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecied of the true Chriſtian Church, as you may ſee in their marginal notes upon the English Bible edit. 1576. in Eſay 60. verſ. ult. And in Daniel 2. verſ. 45. This argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made ſo great impreſſion upon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the moſt learned Proteſtant writers, (who had reſolued not to be Papiſts) that ſom of them turned Iewes, others Atheiſts, others Turks; as <hi>Bernardin Ochin, Seba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Caſtalio, Dauid George, Adam Neuſerus, Allemanus,</hi> and others.</p>
                  <p>Q. Sir though I doubt not of your ſincere dealing, yet I muſt not take upon your ſingle credit, that learned Proteſtants
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:184324:61"/>could turn Turks and Iewes, vpon the ſcore you mention.</p>
                  <p>A. Sir I hope you will belieue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Read Bernardin <hi>Ochins</hi> Preface to his Dialogues, wherin you will find theſe words, <hi>vvhen I did conſider hovv Chriſt by his povver, vviſdom, and goodneſs had foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and eſtablished his Church, &amp;c. and again diſcerned hovv the ſame vvas utterly ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throvvn, I could not but vvonder, and being deſirous to knovv the cauſe, I found there had bin Popes.</hi> From this conceit of the Popes preuailing againſt Chriſts Church, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded there had bin no ſuch thing as Chriſts Diuinity, and proceeded to teach <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and <hi>Poligamy;</hi> and at length came to be an impure Apoſtata, as the famous <hi>Beza</hi> doth term him in his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe de Poligam. pag. 4. <hi>Impurus ille Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtata Bernardinus Ochinus.</hi> Read likewiſe <hi>Sebaſtian Caſtalios'</hi> own words in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face of the great Latin Bible dedicated to King Eduard 6. which are, <hi>The more I do peruſe the Scriptures, the leſs do I find the ſame</hi> (he meanes the profecies of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of Kings and Nations) <hi>performed, hovvſoeuer you underſtand the ſame profecies.</hi> Dauid George (ſay the Proteſtant Diuines of Baſil in their Hiſtory of him edit. 1568.)
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:184324:62"/>diſcourſed thus, <hi>If the doctrin of Chriſt and his Apoſtles had bin true and perfect, the Church vvhich they planted, &amp;c. should haue continued, &amp;c. But novv it is manifeſt that Antichriſt hath ſubuerted the doctrin of the Apoſtles, and the Church by them begun, as is euident in the Papacy: therfore the doctrin of the Apoſtles vvas falſe, and imperfect</hi> And ſo this proteſtant Apoſtle of Baſil, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting vpon the fundamental principle of the <hi>Reformation</hi> (which is a ſuppoſition that the true Church and doctrin had bin inuiſible or deſtroyd for many ages by Popery) became a blaſphemous Apoſtat, affirming that our Sauior was a ſeducer. In like manner <hi>Adam Neuſerus,</hi> the chief Paſtor of Heidelberg, turnd Turk and was circumciſed at Conſtantinople. See Oſian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in his Epitom. Centur. 16. pag. 818. The like fate had <hi>Alemannus, Beza</hi> his boſom friend, as Conradus Schluſſerburg ſayes in Theol. Caluin. fol. 9. and Beza confeſſeth ep. 65. pag. 108. <hi>Alemannum affirmant ad Iudaiſmum defeciſſe.</hi> And all their conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to ſo damn'd ſects, were grounded vpon their not finding any pagan Kings or Nations to haue bin euer conuerted to proteſtancy, but all wayes to popery.</p>
                  <p>Q. I muſt confeſs Sir, that if all the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:184324:62"/>Heathen Kings and Nations haue bin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted to that Chriſtianity which we call popery, and this was performed by Papiſts (which could not be don without mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles) and no pagan Kings and Nations haue bin euer conuerted to Proteſtancy, nor by Proteſtants, yee haue much more to ſay for yourſelues than euer I heard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and we much leſs. But I doubt you will hardly proue that untill the end of the firſt 600. years, there were any Kings or Nations conuerted to Popery; though afterwards I muſt own, that profeſſion was ſpread ouer the world, and reignd untill our Proteſtant Reformation began in the year 1517. And to auoyd prolixity, I deſire you to roſolue me this one queſtion, whether <hi>Conſtantin</hi> the great the firſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Emperor was a Papiſt? Vve belieue that he, and the Church of his time, was Proteſtant, becauſe the pureſt Chriſtianity, (Proteſtancy) was then in vogue; though afterwards it degenerated inſenſibly into Popery.</p>
                  <p>A.
<note place="margin">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Euſeb. de Vita Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantini l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 47. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 38. <hi>S. Hieron. contra Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te med. Coſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Impe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rator sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>c<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quias An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreae, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae, &amp; Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothei tranſtulit Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinopolim, apud quas Daemones rugiunt. And ibid. Si reliqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Sancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre, &amp; in aureos loculos re condere non licet, ſacrilegus fuit cum Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tino Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copi non ſolum ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegi, ſed &amp; fatui iudicandi, qui rem viliſſima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; cineres diſſolut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>n ſeric<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>, vaſe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reo porta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerunt, &amp;c.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>S. Auguſt. tom.</hi> 39. <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Sanctis, ſaith, Crucis caracter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Baſilicae dedicantur, altaria conſecrantur.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>S. Greg. apud Bedam hiſt. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 30.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Euſeb. de vitâ Conſtantini. l</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>atque interdum vultum ſalutari illa paſſionis ſignavit nota.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Zozomen. hiſt. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>Sanctae Crucis plurimum tribuit honoris.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Prudentius in Apotheoſi, vexillum<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> Crucis ſummus Dominator adorat.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>S. Chryſoſtom. in ep.</hi> 2. <hi>Cor. hom.</hi> 26. <hi>verſus fin. Nam &amp; ipſe qui pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puram indutus eſt, accedit illa amplexus ſepulchra, &amp; faſtu depoſito, ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Sanctis ſupplicaturus, ut pro ſe ad Dominum intercedant.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>See the ſame alſo in S. Chryſoſt ad pop. hom.</hi> 60. <hi>verſus finem.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </note> That <hi>Conſtantin</hi> the great was a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, and the Religion then in vogue (and the only then called Catholik) was Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, is euident by <hi>Euſebius</hi> his Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory written a litle after Conſtantins
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:184324:63"/>death, as alſo, by what the <hi>Centuriſts</hi> of <hi>Magdeburg</hi> and all other learned Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants confeſs. For, it is euident by their writings, that Conſtantin erected Temples in memory of Martyrs, and the Apoſtles; prouided his Sepulchre there, to the end that after his death he might be made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of the prayers there offered: He tranſlated to Conſtantinople the reliques of St Andrew, Luke, and Timothy, at which the Deuil did roare, which parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular circumſtance St <hi>Hierom</hi> preſſeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Vigilantius,</hi> whom he concludeth an heretik, for being againſt the praying to Saints, and worshiping their reliques. St Auguſtin and St Gregory (two other Doctors of the Church) defend the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of conſecrating Churches (when Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantin built them) with the ſign of the Croſs, and ſprinkling of holy water, which I belieue the proteſtant Clergy of Dublin were ignorant of, when (as I haue bin credibly informed) they framed (very la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely) a new form of their own heads, to conſecrat M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Lingars</hi> oual Temple, with ſuch hatred to the Croſs, that they would not make uſe of the ſign therof in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, nor bleſs themſelues in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, or throughout the whole work,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:184324:63"/>nor place any Croſs in the top of the Church, for fear of profaning it, or trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling the Spirit of that peaceble Miniſter, not long before departed: Nay Croſſes we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re pull'd down in that Dioceſs, and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liks punished for oppoſing them who committed ſuch ſacrileges.</p>
                  <p>Vvithout doubt <hi>Conſtantin</hi> the great was one of the moſt rank Papiſts, and though he was the man who pulled down <hi>Idols,</hi> and eſtablished Chriſtianity in the world with its ſplendor, and publik exerciſe, yet I feare our Zealous Dublinian Clergy will proteſt againſt his Religion as ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, and cenſure him guilty of Idolatry, when they heare how often he bleſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, making the ſign of the Croſs in his forhead, nay (which is worſe) not only adorning, but adoring (with an inferior religious worship) the Croſs; and (which is worſt of all) <hi>praying to St Peter and Paul
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:184324:64"/>that they vvould be Interceſſors for him to God.</hi> At leaſt the Church of England will not challenge him, as a member of theirs, he being ſo auerſe to the ſpiritual ſupremacy, and Eccleſiaſtical iuriſdiction of temporal ſoueraigns, that he would not ſit down at the Councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> untill the Bishops had therto giuen their aſſent, nor would he take vpon him to iudge of Eccleſiaſtical cauſes, ſaying, <hi>God hath ordained you Bishops, and hath giuen you povver to iudge of your<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, by meanes vvherof vve yeeld ourſelues to your iudgment.</hi> So <hi>Criſpinus</hi> in his book of the eſtate of the Church pag. 99. and Zozomen hiſt. l. c. 10. poſt med. ſets down theſe popish vvords of Conſtantin. <hi>Mihi vero non eſt fas, cum homo ſim, ciuſmodi cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarum cognitionem arrogare, &amp;c.</hi> He is ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore curſed by the Proteſtant vvriters, as bearing the mark of the beaſt, in acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging the Popes ſupremacy, and for ſubduing all Chriſtian Churches to his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction; ſo <hi>Frigiuillaeus in his palma Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiana</hi> dedicated to Q. Elizabeth pag. 35. ſaying, that Conſtantin, <hi>preferred the Bishops of Rome, and Conſtantinople before others, yet attributed the Primacy before all to the Roman.</hi> And pag. 34. ſaith, that <hi>Conſtantin gaue the povver of the beaſt to Pope Iulius, vvhich
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:184324:64"/>Iulius preſently exerciſed; for Conſtantin alſo carried the mark of the Dragon in his armes, &amp;c.</hi> And M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Napper</hi> in his Treatiſe vpon th Reuelations dedicated to King <hi>Iames,</hi> ſaith, <hi>After the year of God</hi> 300. <hi>the Emperor Conſtantin ſubdued all Chriſtian Churches to Pope Silueſter; from vvhich time till theſe our dayes the Pope and his Clergy hath poſſeſſed the outvvard and viſible Church.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Q. Pardon Sir, that I interrupt you from proceeding further in the Proof of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantins being a Papiſt. I am fully conuinc't he was of your Popish Religion, and ſeing M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Napper</hi> ſayes to King Iames, that Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery poſſeſſed and gouerned the viſible Church euer ſince that time, I would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly know whether it was ſo before <hi>Conſtantins</hi> time, or whether that Emperor beſtowed this ſupremacy vpon the Pope, and pulld down Proteſtancy to ſet up Popery?</p>
                  <p>A. To ſatisfy your curioſity I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit you to your own Proteſtant writers, the Centuriſts and others. I will only tell you that one of the moſt learneſt prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant writers called <hi>Philip Nicolai,</hi> took great pains in this matter, in his work <hi>de regno Chriſti,</hi> undertaking to diſcouer the firſt beginning and increaſe of the papal
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:184324:65"/>dignity, or ſupremacy, and concludeth at laſt with theſe words pag. 221. <hi>Primatus af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectatio, communis fuit infirmitas Apoſtolorum, ac etiam primorum Vrbis Romae Epiſcoporum.</hi> The affectation of the Primacy was an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity common to the Apoſtles, as alſo to the firſt Bishops of Rome. M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Midleton</hi> likewiſe in his Papiſtomaſtix, pag. 193. ſaith, <hi>that peruſing Councells, Fathers, and ſtories from the Apoſtles forvvord, vve find the print of the Popes feet.</hi> Vve may therfore follow ſecurely ſteps ſo ancient and ſo au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentik. If Popery were not the right way to heauen, certainly the ancient Councells would haue condemn'd it, the Fathers would haue declin'd it, and the Hiſtories would haue recounted how it entred into the Church, and ſupplanted the former Religion that Chriſt and the Apoſtles had preach't. And yet not a vvord of this chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge, or corruption in Councells, Fathers, or any Hiſtory. This is the greateſt of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, that the doctrin and publik profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Popery, being in itſelf ſo contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Proteſtancy (vvhich is ſuppoſed by its Profeſſors to haue bin the pure and primitiue Chriſtianity) should ſteale ſo early, and ſo inſenſibly into the Church, notwithſtanding the vigilancy of thoſe
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:184324:65"/>primitiue Paſtors, and the great concern of euery faithfull, to obſerue and oppoſe the leaſt nouelty whatſoeuer in matters of doctrin; any change or corruption therof inuoluing a damnable hereſy.</p>
                  <p>Q. Though the conuerſion of all hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Kings and Nations were as you ſay to Popery, and performed by Papiſts; and that it is not credible God vvould permit ſo general a peruerſion, vvherby the end of inſtituting his Church would be fruſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, yet I vvould vvillingly know vvhether you can produce any Miracles againſt our Proteſtant doctrin vvherby we differ from the Papiſts.</p>
                  <p>A.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>See D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Humfry in Ieſuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmi p.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>rat.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 627. <hi>Bishop Bale in Act. Rom. Pont. pag.</hi> 44.45. <hi>&amp;</hi> 46. <hi>Oſiand. in Epit. Ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 289. <hi>&amp;</hi> 288. <hi>And the Magdeb. Centur.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 20.</note> All the Miracles that moued the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans to be Papiſts, were wrought againſt Proteſtancy. I will inſtance it in the conuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion of our Saxon Anceſtors, vvho vvere Pagans, and made Papiſts by the preaching and Miracles of St <hi>Auſtin</hi> the Monk, Apoſtle of England. The Proteſtant writers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs he conuerted the Saxons to the <hi>Chaos of Popish Ceremonies, and ſuperſtition,</hi> and ſpecify worship of Images, praying to Saints, Purgatory, Maſs, Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, holy water, &amp;c. And yet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues confeſs with St <hi>Bede,</hi> that his doctrin and that of the ancient Britans of that
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:184324:66"/>time,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>B<hi rend="sup">p</hi>. Iuel in his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant of Popes. B<hi rend="sup">p</hi>. God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin in his Catalogue of Bishops p.</hi> 1. <hi>Fox in his Acts and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. printed</hi> 1576. <hi>pag.</hi> 463.</note> difered only in a ceremony of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and in the day of celebrating Eaſter, St <hi>Auſtin</hi> confirming his own practiſe therin, by a confeſſed Miracle of reſtoring ſight to a blind man. Now it being eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by our English Chronicles, and the Proteſtant vvriters (vvherof M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Iohn Fox,</hi> Bishop <hi>Goduin,</hi> and Bishop <hi>Iuel</hi> are to be particularly noted, as being moſt eminent) that the ancient Britans after receiuing <hi>the Catholik Faith in the Apoſtles time, held the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me untill Auſtins coming, and neuer forſook it for any manner of falſe preaching of other, nor for torments, &amp;c.</hi> It muſt be concluded that the ancient Britans were firſt conuerted to Popery, and ſo continued untill <hi>Auſtins</hi> time, and that his and their doctrin was the ſame in all particulars contrary to Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, and confirmed by Miracles. But becauſe you ſeem to deſire a <hi>dogmatical</hi> Miracle, that is, one vvrought in confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Popery; not only as it is Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in general, but at it is Chriſtianity in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, and oppoſit to Proteſtancy, I will endeu or to ſatisfy your curioſity, hoping therby to ſetle your conſcience.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:184324:66"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. BERNARDS VNDENIABLE Miracles vvrought by God to confound Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, and confirm the doctrin of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of the Maſs, Tranſubſtantiation, Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, Prayer for the dead, Prayer to Saints, their vvorship, and that of Images, Chriſme, the Popes ſupremacy, &amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SAint Bernards learning, ſanctity, and Miracles are ſo generaly confeſſed by all Proteſtant writers that Doctor <hi>Stilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fleet</hi> in his late Comedy of the Idolatry and Fanaticiſm of the Church of Rome, durſt not bring him vpon the ſtage. Vvhitaker <hi>de Eccleſiâ,</hi> pag. 369. ſaith of him, <hi>I do realy belieue Bernard vvas a true Saint.</hi> Oſiander cent. 12. ſaith, <hi>Saint Bernard Abot of Clare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ual vvas a uery pious man, &amp;c. Gomarus in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo Eccleſiae,</hi> pag. 23. ſaith, one pious man <hi>your Church had in many years. Bernard your Saint.</hi> And <hi>Paſquils</hi> return into England pag. 8. &amp; 13. ſaith, <hi>he vvas a good Father and one of the lamps of Gods Church.</hi> He was ſo famous for his learning, humility, deuotion, and Miracles, that after his refuſal of all Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:184324:67"/>dignities, he gouerned not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Church, but the temporal Princes were ſayd by him, and ſubmitted to his iudgment. King Henry 2. of England for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook a Schiſmatical Pope (which he had ſupported againſt the King of France) by ſaint Bernards perſuaſion. The King of France gaue ouer troubling the Bishops for his ſake. <hi>VVilliam</hi> the Duke of Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain was conuerted from a deuouring wolf to a meek Lamb by his words. All the world lookt upon ſaint Bernard as the Apoſtle of that age, wherin diuers here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies were broacht by the <hi>VValdenſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>S. Bern. Ep.</hi> 241. <hi>ad Toloſ ſaith, vve thank God for that our comming to you vvas not in uain, our ſtay indeed vvas short vvith you, but not nn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfull; the truth being by us made manifeſt</hi> (non ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mone ſed etiam in vi tute) <hi>not only by prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, but alſo by povver</hi> of vvorking Miracles <hi>the Vvol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues are depren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolici, Henricians,</hi> and others. Theſe two laſt Sects had infected a great part of France, eſpecialy about <hi>Tolouſe;</hi> their chief errors vvere againſt Tranſubſtantiation, Prayers to Saints, and the ſame vvhich Proteſtants hold in our dayes, and we haue mentioned in the title of this Chapter. The Pope ſent a Legat, and St Bernard, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute them. In this Miſſion, amongſt innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable others, he vvrought the enſuing Miracle, not only vvritten by his Diſciple <hi>Godifridus,</hi> who was an eye witneſs ther of, but recorded in the other Hiſtories of that time, and inſinuated by St Bernard himſelf in his 241. Epiſtle to the people of <hi>Tolouſe,</hi>
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:184324:67"/>to the end they might be conſtant in the <hi>manifeſt</hi> doctrin vvhich he had preacht againſt the <hi>Henricians,</hi> vvhom Proteſtants challenge as members and Martyrs of the Proteſtant Church, as euery one may ſee in their <hi>Catalogue of the vvitneſſes of truth,</hi> printed 1597. and in M. Symondes upon the Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, pag. 142. and 143. The Miracle is recounted by <hi>Godefridus invitâ Bern. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5. and by others of the ſame time, as follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth.</p>
               <p>There is a place in the Country of Tolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa, called <hi>Sarlatum,</hi> vvhere after the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon vvas don, they offerd to he ſeruant of God (as euery vvhere the uſe vvas) many loaues to bleſs, vvihich he, lifting up his hand, and making the ſign of the Croſs, in Gods name bleſſing, ſayd thus. <hi>In this you shall Knovv that theſe things are true vvhich vvee, and that thoſe other are falſe vvhich the heretiks labor to perſuade you; that vvhoſoeuer they be (of your diſeaſed perſons) that taſt the loaues: they shall be healed, to the end you may Knovv us to be the true Miniſter of God.</hi> The Bishop of Chartres (a great friend to the Saint) thinking this propoſition too general, told the people, they vvere to underſtand, it conditionaly, ſo they did cate of the loaues vvith Faith. St Bernard
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:184324:68"/>ſudenly replied, <hi>My Lord, I do not mean ſo, my meaning and ſaying is, that all ſick folks vvho vvill eat of thoſe loaues, shall recouer their health, to the end it may be Knovven vve are Gods true Miniſters.</hi> And acordingly it fell out, not one diſeaſed perſon, that did eat of the bread, miſt of being eured; and the Miracle being thus diuulged, by its ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, ſo huge a multitude of people came to thank and admire the Saint; that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined the common roads, and vvent by by wayes to Tolouſe; vvhere at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Catholiks, and to further confute the aforeſaid heteſies againſt Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, Maſs, Purgatory, prayer to Saints, vvorship of Images, &amp;c. he vvith giuing his benediction to a paralitik prieſt that lay a dying in the College of St <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nin,</hi> reſtored him to ſo perfect health, that the Prieſt (vvho alſo vvas called Bernard) ſudenly roſe out of his bed vvhere he had bin immoueable a long time, followed the Saint, and begd of him to be admitted into the number of his Monks; vvhich vvas granted, and afterwards liued amongſt them very religiouſly, and vvas at length Abot of <hi>Valdeau.</hi> Vvith theſe Miracles the heretiks vvere confounded, and ſo many conuerted, that their ſeducer <hi>Henricus</hi> hid
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:184324:68"/>himſelf, and finding no refuge among thoſe who formerly had followed him, he was taken priſoner, and preſented in chains before the Bishop.</p>
               <p>Q. If God wrought ſuch Miracles as theſe for the conuerſion of the <hi>Henricians</hi> and other heretiks (as you call them) of that age, why may not we Proteſtants ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that he will do the ſame for our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion, if we be in errors. I am ſure we deſire to ſaue our Souls: And certainly God is as willing to ſaue us as any others. I wish we could ſee ſuch Miracles wrought by any Bernard, or other Saint. Vve should ſoon be Papiſts.</p>
               <p>A. One of the reaſons vvhy God doth not vvork now ſuch Miracles for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of Proteſtants, is, becauſe he hath vvrought them for the <hi>Henricians:</hi> For, the ſame errors againſt <hi>Tranſubſtantiation, Maſs, Prayer to Saints,</hi> Vvorship of <hi>Images,</hi> &amp;c. being common to both ſects, the ſame Miracles confute both equaly, and may now conuince Proteſtants, as vvell as they did anciently the <hi>Henricians,</hi> of heretical and damnable obſtinacy. And therfore its not likely Proteſtants vvould becom Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, though they had ſeen an other St <hi>Bernard</hi> work the ſame Miracles to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:184324:69"/>the Roman Catholik Faith againſt Proteſtancy; that in effect hauing bin don againſt it in the caſe of the <hi>Henricians.</hi> I am the more apt to belieue the ſight of ſuch Prodigies vvould not conuert you, becauſe your Proteſtant Authors grant the matter of fact of St Bernards Miracles againſt the <hi>Henricias</hi> doctrin, and of S. Dominik againſt the <hi>Albige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes Tenets</hi> (wherin theſe alſo agre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vvith Proteſtants) and only anſwer that they vvere Antichriſtian Miracles, wrought by the Deuills power to confirm the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of the Maſs, and Images, &amp;c. or at leaſt they were feigned by idle Monks. Take it in their own words.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>See the Ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>turiſts, and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiander in Epitom. cent.</hi> 9.10.11. <hi>pag.</hi> 213.</note> 
                  <hi>The Miracles vvhich ſuperſtitious Monks relate, are either feigned by themſelues, or vvrought by Satans en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments, and therfore ought to be enliſted amongſt Antichriſts Miracles becauſe they vvere vvrought to confirm manifeſt Idolatry, and to eſtablish the vvicked vvorship of Images, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of Reliques, Inuocation of Saints, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of Maſs, &amp;c.</hi> True it is that Oſian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſpeaking of Saint Bernards Miracles, Cent. 12. pag. 310. ſaith, <hi>Not that I think St Bernard vvas a Magitian, but that I think it probable Satan vvrought the Miracles, vvherby the Saint himſelf and others vvere deceiued.</hi> And this is the common anſwer
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:184324:69"/>all Proteſtants giue to our Miracles, when they can not deny the fact, nor diſcouer any fraud. And certaintly they would giue now the ſame anſwer to the moſt euident and undeniable Miracles, if any were wrought before theyr eyes.</p>
               <p>Q. Am I who can not read, or under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Latin and other languages, wherin all this you ſay and quote, is written, bound to belieue the matter of fact, and conform therunto my Faith? Vvhat if a Proteſtant Miniſter or Bishop tells me all you ſay are lyes? Vvhom muſt I belieue? Or am I obliged under pain of damnation to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect his ſincerity and doctrin, if he will not encounter you, or any other who of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers to make good vvhat you ſay, by she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing the paſſages in the books them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues? I confeſs I think I am. Howeuer I pray tell me vvhat I ought to do in ſuch a caſe.</p>
               <p>A. You ſee how in leſs than two hours time you may know by your Bishops or Miniſters carriage and courage in exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning any plain book that relates Miracles and matter of fact, vvhether the Proteſtant Religion be true or falſe. If he will reſolue to conferr, or rather to conſter the vvords of the book, you vvill eaſily iudge of the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:184324:70"/>truth by their ſenſe: to which you muſt keep him (and the Catholik alſo) without any other digreſſions, or diſcourſes: all your buiſneſs muſt be, to know vvhether the Miracle or matter of fact be ſo in the book as I told you; and that, you may know from any honeſt man vvho can read and underſtand it, as vvell (perhaps bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) than from your Proteſtant Miniſter or Bishop.</p>
               <p>As for the anſwers vvhich the moſt learned Proteſtants giue to the argument of our miracles, they are ſo vveak, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne but vvicked and obſtinat perſons can be ſatisfied ther with. Their firſt anſwer is, that our miracles haue bin feigned by idle Monks. This is ſo damnd an anſwer that they dare not ſtick to it, becauſe it is not poſſible that ſuch publik tranſactions as St Bernards, or St Dominiks preaching, and Miracles againſt the <hi>Henricians</hi> and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigenſes,</hi> could be impoſed vpon the world, there being as many Obſeruers as there vvere perſons either curious, or concernd in two ſo contrary parties. Vvhy did not ſom one of the <hi>Henricians,</hi> or <hi>Albigenſes</hi> publish and declare the impoſture, vvhen their Religion vvas ſo diſcredited therby? Vvhy should Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> 3. venter to
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:184324:70"/>be laught at, and depoſed from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolik ſee for canonizing St <hi>Bernard,</hi> 12. years after his death, if his Miracles vvere not ſo authentik, that they could not be contradicted? Vvhat deſign could the world and that age haue in conſpiring to impoſe ſuch Miracles vpon their friends and poſterity, and in damning themſelues therby, for St <hi>Bernards</hi> ſake? The ſame argument may be applied to St <hi>Dominik,</hi> St <hi>Francis,</hi> St <hi>Vincent Ferrer,</hi> St <hi>Francis Xauier,</hi> or to any other of our Roman Church, vvhoſe miracles haue bin vvrought in publik aſſemblies, and not contradicted as falſe or fraudulent by any of thoſe ages that vvere vvitneſſes to them, or vvherin they vvere firſt ſpoke of. And this is of ſuch force, that our Proteſtant. Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries grant it to be true, and therfore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr to the Deuills power for their anſwer, and the confutation of our Miracles, as the obſtinat Iewes did againſt them of Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:184324:71"/>
               <head>VVHETHER TRADITION, TOGETHER vvith the Miracles of Chriſt and of the Church do demonſtrat or undeniably conclude that God reueald the articles of Chriſtian Faith; Or vvhether they only demonſtrat, or cleerly proue, that vve are obliged under pain of damnation to belieue that God reuea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them? And vvhether it be <hi>cleerly</hi> eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, or more than moraly euident, that they are true ſupernatural Miracles?</head>
               <p>Q. I do think the <hi>Parallell</hi> between Chriſts Miracles and thoſe of the Roman Catholik Church, or between the obſtinat Iewes and the Proteſtants, doth not hold. Chriſts Miracles vvere ſo eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſupernatural or Diuine, that if the obſtinat Iewes vvould conſider the viſible circumſtances therof, they could not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny them to be true and Diuine Miracles. But the Miracles of the Roman Catholik Church (I ſpeake of the moſt authentik) are no ſuch; for, vve Proteſtants examin and conſider all the circumſtances of them, and yet vve can, and do deny them to be true Diuine Miracles.</p>
               <p>A. The parallell doth hold, and you will
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:184324:71"/>think ſo if you reflect upon it. 1. It is a miſtake to belieue that Chriſts Miracles were ſo cleerly ſupernatural and Diuine as to force an aſſent or acknowledgment of their being ſo, from the Iewes and Gentils that ſaw them (and therfore could not but admire them, and conſider their ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing circumſtances.) For, if the Miracles had appeared to them ſupernatural and undeniably true, no aſſent of their Faith could be a free act; and that vvherwith St Peter own'd Chriſts Diuinity,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 16.</note> and for vvhich he deſerued to be made the Rock or foundation of the Church, vvould not haue bin ſo particularly applauded, and rewarded by Chriſt himſelf; the other Apoſtles hauing ſeen and conſidered as much as he the Miracles of Chriſt vvhich moued St Peter to that Confeſſion of Faith, and yet no aſſent of Chriſts Diuinity flowed neceſſarily from that their ſight and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; neither vvas it forc't from St Peter; but vvas a free act and aſſent of his (after ſeing all the Miracles and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their circumſtances) to ſay, <hi>Thou art Chriſt, Son of the liuing God.</hi> The obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat Iewes therfore did conſider all cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of Chriſts perſon and Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles as much as thoſe vvho belieued them
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:184324:72"/>to be Diuine, nay more, becauſe the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, Phariſees, and the Doctors of the law ſearcht and pry'd more narowly into his actions, and were better able to iudge of their being natural or ſupernatural, than moſt of thoſe, who belieued his Miracles vvere Diuine, and himſelf the <hi>Meſsias.</hi> And this appeareth in many paſſages, as in that of the blind man, vvhom they caſt out of the Synagogue; for they underſtood the Miracle better than himſelf, and vvere ſufficiently conuinc't of the cure, and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of fact. It vvas not therfore vvant of conſideration of the circumſtances of Chriſts perſon and Miracles that made the learned Iewes obſtinat, but their abundan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of pride, vvhich made them auerſe from ſubmitting their iudgments to Chriſts doctrin, notwithſtanding they had moral euidence of the Diuinity of his perſon and of the ſupernaturality of his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles.</p>
               <p>Q. I can not comprehend how Chriſts Miracles or any others, can oblige men to belieue his doctrin, or conuince them of obſtinacy and hereſy, for not belieuing it and his Diuinity, unleſs it be firſt made cleerly and undeniably euident to them, that the Miracles are true and ſuperna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural.
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:184324:72"/>As for your <hi>Moral euidence</hi> of their being true Miracles, it is not ſtrong en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough to build therupon ſo abſolute an aſſurance as is requiſit in our acts or aſſents of Chriſtian Faith, vvhich excludes all doubts, and euen all moral poſſibility of falſood.</p>
               <p>A. I often told you that the certainty and aſſurance of Chriſtian Faith is not grounded vpon the euidence of Chriſts Miracles (or any others of his Church) being true Miracles; or of its <hi>Tradition</hi> being infallible; but upon Gods <hi>Veracity,</hi> vvhich is ſo infinitly auers from all Kind of falſood, that he will no more permit any to be ſo probably and plauſibly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered upon him as the Roman doctrin is, than poſitiuely promote it. Now, Chriſts Diuinity and the doctrin of the Roman Catholik Church being confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by ſuch prodigies and ſigns as haue a moral euidence of being ſupernatural and true Miracles, this makes it moraly euident to all men, that none but God is Author of that doctrin and of the prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies which confirm it. This moral euiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of God being the Author, is not indeed (as you ſay) ſtrong enough to beare and ground upon itſelf the aſſurance of an
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:184324:73"/>aſſent or act of Chriſtian Faith; but it is a prudent and ſufficient inducement to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue moſt certaintly, and without any Kind of doubt, that God would not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſo great an appearance of his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity as the miracles of Chriſt and of the Roman Church manifeſtly shew to all the world, to be a cheat, or any thing leſs than his own great Seal; wherfore at the ſight therof all men are bound under pain of damnation to belieue God alone is the Author of Chriſts and the Roman Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Miracles and doctrin, iuſt as ſubiects are bound under pain of death to obey the King and Magiſtrats Orders, when ſigned and ſealed with the uſual and authentik marks of their ſupreme authority. They are bound I ſay to obey, though they haue only moral euidence that he is King, and that his Seal and Orders are true, and not conterfeit.</p>
               <p>Q. Methinks this argument may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torted againſt your ſelf. For, if notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the moral euidence we haue of ſuch perſons being our Parents, or law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Kings; and of their ſeales and Orders not being counterfeit, we are bound on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to honor, and obey them in our outward actions; but wee are not bound to aſſent
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:184324:73"/>inwardly without any Kind of doubt, that ſuch men are our Parents, or our legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mat Kings; or that their hands and ſeales are not counterfeit: If, I ſay, this moral euidence can not oblige us to ſuch inward aſſurances and aſſents, how can the moral euidence of Chriſts and the Roman Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Miracles being true and ſupernatural Miracles, oblige us under pain of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to belieue (vvithout any Kind of doubt) Chriſts Diuinity, and the Roman Catholik doctrin? At leaſt this much fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth from hence, that the moral euiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of the aforſaid Miracles and ſigns of the Church, can only exact from us an outward conformity to its decrees, not an inward aſſent to its doctrin.</p>
               <p>A. The extent of euery authority ought to be meaſured by its appearance. If its appearance be only human or natural, it reacheth no further than to regular thoſe outward moral actions which are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for the gouernment and peace of the Commonwealth; it hath not any thing to do vvith directing the ſoul by inward acts and undoubted aſſents to its ſupernatural end. If the appearence of the authority be ſupernatural, and moraly euident to us, (by prodigies, profecies, or other viſible
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:184324:74"/>ſigns) that it is ſo, then it claimes a iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction ouer the ſoul, and may exact from it ſuch inward acts and aſſents as are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable to that ſupernatural end for vvhich God hath inſtituted his Church, and adornd it vvith thoſe Diuine marks and miracles vvhich Chriſt himſelf mentions, Marc. 16. and haue bin viſible in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholik euer ſince the Apoſtles. This undeniable <hi>Maxim</hi> being layd as a foundation, there can be no difficulty in ſeing the diſparity there is between the human authority of Commonwealths, and the ſpiritual and ſupernatural of the Church, by virtue of their different ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances; the miracles and ſigns of the Church making ſo ſupernatural a shew as to declare God alone is the Author of its doctrin and authority, is extended to the ſoul, and to the inward acts and aſſents therof, regulating them as it is fit for the ſaluation of mankind. No human or natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral authority of Kings or temporal Princes can reach ſo far, becauſe the appearance therof is only natural.</p>
               <p>Q. Vvill not the appearance of Anti-Chriſts Miracles be ſupernatural? Did not thoſe of the Magitians of Egipt look like ſupernatural, and indiſcernable from tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:184324:74"/>of Moyſes? How then can a ſupernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral appearance, or a moral euidence of prodigies being true Miracles, exact or pretend to any authority ouer our inward acts of the will and underſtanding? shall we ſubmit our iudgments to Anti-Chriſts doctrin, becauſe his Miracles will ſeem to be ſupernatural. If not, why ſhould we ſubmit our iudgments to the Roman Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholik Church, becauſe its moſt authentik Miracles ſeem to be ſupernatural?</p>
               <p>A. This argument only proues that true Miracles (euen thoſe of Chriſt) do not cleerly euidence or conclude their own <hi>ſupernaturality,</hi> or their being true Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. It is ſo hard a matter to diſtinguish between true and falſe or Anti Chriſtian Miracles, that our Sauior ſayes, euen the elect would be ſeduced by the laſt, if for their ſake, and by Gods particular proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence thoſe dayes would not be short<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and therfore he warnes his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and all the faithfull to beware of Anti-Chriſts Miracles, for reſſembling ſo much his own; and giues certain ſigns wherby men may diſcouer that he who works them, is Anti-Chriſt. Chriſts Miracles therfore (as thoſe alſo of the Church) being firſt, and as it were in poſſeſſion
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:184324:75"/>of Gods authority, by being his great ſeale, and confirming his doctrin, do by that precedency and Chriſts prediction of conterfeit Miracles, manifeſt their ſupernaturality in a different manner from Antichriſts and all other lying pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies, which haue bin or will be wrought to confirm any doctrin contrary to that of the Catholik Church. Out of all which we conclude that euen Chriſts Miracles, and <hi>à fortiori</hi> thoſe of the Church (if ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken without his prediction and their own precedency) do not cleerly euidence to us that they are true Miracles, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence can not cleerly euidence to us the Diuinity of Chriſt, or that God reuealed the articles of Chriſtian Religion. And the ſame muſt be ſayd of Catholik <hi>Tradition,</hi> euen as it is confirmed by theſe Miracles of the Church. So that this Tradition is not the <hi>Motiue,</hi> but the <hi>Rule</hi> of Faith, vvhich directs us infallibly (though not cleerly) to Gods reuelations; and therfore doth not demonſtrat, or undeniably conclude that euer God reuealed any one article of that Faith; though the ſame Tradition, as confirmed by the ſigns of the Church, doth demonſtrat or at leaſt undeniably proue, that we are obliged under pain of
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:184324:75"/>damnation to belieue (and that moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly) that God reuealed euery point which the Roman Catholik Church doth propoſe as an article of Faith. This much of Miracles in general. Now let us return to Saint Bernards, and conſider it in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</p>
               <p>St Bernard makes the ſame propoſal to the <hi>Henricians</hi> and people about Tolouſe, that <hi>Elias</hi> made to the Iewes, and <hi>Baaliſts.</hi> He appeald to Gods omnipotency for the manifeſtation of the truth. And ſpoke with ſuch confidence of ſucceſs, as if the attempt of the miracle had not only bin conſulted with God, but had bin com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by him. Conſider now, I pray, whether it be credible to any perſon that hath common ſenſe, or whether it be conſiſtent with Gods infinit veracity and goodneſs, that vpon ſo publik a trial of both, and wherof depended the damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or ſaluation of ſo many Souls, God would play the <hi>Neuter,</hi> and permit the Deuill abuſe the ſincerity and ſanctity of Saint Bernard to ſeduce the poor ſimple people by working Miracles, which ſaint Bernard himſelf and the wiſeſt of that age took to be Diuine, and were in appearan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce as much aboue the power of nature, as
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:184324:76"/>thoſe were which Chriſt wrought? If this be as inconſiſtent with common ſenſe, as it is with Chriſtianity, not one illiterat Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant in the world who hath any ſenſe, can be excuſed by inuincible ignorance from damnation, no learned Proteſtant from hereſy. For, hereſy is obſtinacy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt doctrin ſufficiently propoſed as Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine. And if <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> the Maſs, Interceſſion of Saints, worship of Images, Purgatory, &amp;c. be not ſufficiently propoſed as Diuine doctrin by the teſtimony of the Church, and theſe Miracles of St Bernard, and other Roman Catholik Saints; and in a coniuncture that the ſame doctrin was as much queſtioned by the <hi>Henricians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Aug. l.</hi> 22. <hi>de Ciuit. Dei c.</hi> 8. <hi>ad ſanctu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Martyrem orare per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rexerunt, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>He that belieueth in me, the vvorks, that I do, he shall do, and greater. Ioan.</hi> 14.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Nazian. in Epitaph. Gorgoniae. Orat.</hi> II. <hi>ſaith,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Proſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf before the Altar, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling upon him vvho vvas honoured and vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, O admirable thing! she preſently felt her ſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from her ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>neſs, and ſo she returned eaſed both in body and mind &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </note> as now it is by Proteſtants, neuer any doctrin hath bin yet ſufficiently propoſed as Diuine; nay not the doctrin of <hi>Elias,</hi> nor of Chriſt himſelf; becauſe neither hath bin confirmed by greater Miracles than ours. I need not repeat others more ancient, as that (which St Auſtin ſayes he was wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of) when <hi>Palladia</hi> recouered her ſight by praying to St Steuen; or that vvhich St <hi>Gregory</hi> Nazianzen recounts of his ſiſter <hi>Gorgonia</hi> recouering ſudenly her health, by adoring the bleſſed Sacrament vpon the Altar; or that of the Image of Chriſt
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:184324:76"/>erected by the woman he cured of her flux, wherof ſee Euſebius hiſt. lib. 7. c. 14. or that of the Crucifix in <hi>Berito,</hi> alleged in 2. Concill. Niſſen. act. 4. or that recounted by <hi>Optatus, l,</hi> 1. <hi>contra Donatiſtas,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the reſeruing and taking the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in one Kind; as alſo the holy oyle, or Chriſme; or that of the perſon raiſed from death to receiue the <hi>extreme Vnction,</hi> mentioned by St Bernard in vit. Malach. Or that of <hi>Confeſsion</hi> related by St Bede hiſt. l. 5. cap. 14. Theſe and innumerable others, are ſuperfluous, ſeing thoſe of St Bernard are ſufficient to conuince that no Proteſtant, who hath ſo much ſenſe as to belieue Gods goodneſs and veracity, can be ſaued, if he denyes any one particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of the Roman Catholik doctrin, when he is credibly informed that this authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is confirmed by ſuch Miracles as thoſe of Saint Bernard, and other Saints of our Church, which are related in the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blik Acts and Proceſs of their Canoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="address">
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:184324:77"/>
               <head>AN HVMBLE ADRESS To the Honorable Houſe of Commons.</head>
               <p>MAy it pleaſe you, Honorable Sirs, who are the Preſeruers of our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties (except the chief, which is that of conſcience) to take in good part, that the meaneſt of his Maieſties ſubiects hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beg of you to conſider, whether it be not a damnable ſin, to perſecute Souls for profeſſing the Religion of your Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Anceſtors, confirmed by ſo many credible ſigns of Gods approbation and protection, that the wiſeſt and warieſt men of the whole world (both in this and former ages) were conuinc't they were true Miracles; and yourſelues haue no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to belieue the contrary, but that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudice wherunto the principles of your education from your infancy, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of your Teachers led you, before you could diſcern the truth of their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trin, or the intricacy of their deſign. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect I beſeech you, upon the frailty of your Miniſters, and the fallibility of your Church, and weigh with yourſelues, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be not more credible that your
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:184324:77"/>English Congregation ſeaſoned with two ſuch <hi>Ingredients</hi> as <hi>frailty</hi> and <hi>fallibility,</hi> may be miſtaken in myſteries of Faith, than that God would permit the whole Catholik world, and ſuch men as Saint Bernard, and the other Roman Catholik Saints, to be deluded and ſeduced by the Deuils lying prodigies; and that, in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture when Gods veracity and honor Iay at the ſtake in a publik trial of true and falſe doctrin. Vvould any of yourſelues ſtand by in ſuch an occaſion as an idle ſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tator, or unconcerned perſon, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a Rogue or a Fool clad in your liuery, produce counterfeit letters, and deliuer ſeditious orders in your name? Vvould any of you ſuffer poor people who wish you well, to be deſtroyd by ſuch wicked practiſes? Vvould you condeſcend ſo far with your greateſt Ennemy, as to wink at his malice, and at the uniuſt meanes he applied to ruin your well meaning Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants; or friends? Certainly you would diſclaim in the fourbery, and neuer wink at a fraud ſo preiudicial to the people, and as contrary to your noble inclinations, as to the principles of honor, and truth which you profeſs.</p>
               <p>Be pleaſed then to haue as good an opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:184324:78"/>of Gods inclination to honor and truth, as of your own. Let not the firſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions vpon your tender undiſcerning years, grown at unawares into a ſettleneſs through education and cuſtom blind your riper and more manly iudgments to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded, God can permit ſuch Miracles as we haue recounted, to be only miſtakes of the Roman Church, and human or Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical artifices; or that he would ſuffer his greateſt Enemy to ſeduce innocent Souls by cheats ſo like ſupernatural ſeales of the Diuine doctrin and miniſtery, that ſuch prudent, learned, and conſcientious men as the Roman Catholik Church hath had in all ages, could (after a ſeuere ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny) conclude to be the work of Gods omnipotency, and aboue the power of all natural cauſes. This well conſidered, will, I hope, make you more Kind to your Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholik Kindred and Neighbors, and to the Religion of all your Anceſtors before Queen Elizabeths reign. But if you ſlight this humble aduice, grounded vpon ſo cleer euidence, I feare that God, who is a jealous God, and no leſs concerned for his honor, and veracity, than infinit good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and an infinit auerſion from falſood inclines him to be, will viſit you in the
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:184324:78"/>fury of his iuſtice, and deny to you in your greateſt need, that mercy which yee deny to tender conſciences; he will heare the loud cryes of innocent bloud which pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trat the Heauens, when they find no relief vpon earth. God direct you in all your wayes, and reſolutions; and make us ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thankfull for your moderation, or ſtrengthen us with conſtancy and patience againſt your perſecution.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb facs="tcp:184324:79"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:184324:79"/>
            <head>AN APPENDIX.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>HOVV RATIONAL IT IS NOT to exact more then moral euidence in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Faith. The Author of <hi>Sure footings</hi> doctrin în that particular explaind by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and vindicated from the Cenſure of the deceaſed Author of <hi>Religion and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Q. No body queſtions but that Gods reuelation and authority if it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res ſufficiently applyed to the Church pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing and deciding matters of Faith, doth oblige all men (euen the moſt ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous and ſubtile Doubters and Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) to ſubmit their iudgments and inward aſſents therunto. My doubt is, whether the Diuine reuelation and authority can be ſufficiently applyed to the Church un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs we ſee that application proued by cleer and concluſiue euidence? As for your often repeated Parallell between God and Soueraings, there is a uaſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parity between the Royal and Diuine au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority as to the ſufficiency of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:184324:80"/>The Royal authority is ſufficiently propoſed, as ſuch, by a moral euidence of its application to ſuch as claim to be the Kings Miniſters and Meſſengers; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a King can not giue to his ſubiects greater euidence then moral, that he truſts and employs ſuch men with declaring his pleaſure and commands. But God (wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thout any inconueniency to himſelf) may giue cleer and concluſiue euidence to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry indiuidual perſon that himſelf reueald the doctrin which the Church propoſeth as Diuine. And therfore it ſeems to be uery agreable to reaſon, that in the Church there be ſom Doctors who may demonſtrat, or proue by concluſiue eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence againſt the wittieſt Doubters, that he hath don ſo <hi>de facto,</hi> by virtue of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: ſeing cleer knowledge is not only the ſureſt but the moſt connatural way for rational Creatures to arriue to the happy end we all ayme at by our Faith and actions.</p>
               <p>A. If God can iuſtly oblige the wittieſt men of the vvorld underpain of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to content themſelues with moral euidence (when they haue no greater) of ſuch and ſuch men being their Princes and Parents, and (in conſequence therof)
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:184324:80"/>to ſubmit unto them, and their Miniſters or Meſſengers, their outward actions of greateſt importance; ſure he may juſtly oblige under pain of damnation the ſame men to content themſelues with a moral euidence (if he be pleaſed to giue no grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) for ſubmitting their iudgments (by a moſt certain belief) to his reuelations and authority claimd by the Church, and she<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing for it marks ſo ſupernatural of the Diuine truſt and truth, that they can not be prudently queſtioned as counterfeit. For, as the imperfection of our human nature and Knowledge (as alſo the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue of Soueraignty and ſuperiority) makes it uery reaſonable, and natural enough to us, to be ſubiect and directed in our outward actions by a ſole moral euidence, when we haue no greater; ſo the ſame imperfection (and Gods infinit Excellency) doth demonſtrat that it is moſt reaſonable, and natural to us, to be directed in our inward acts and aſſents by ſupernatural moral euidence, when God is pleaſed to giue us no greater, ſeing we haue no right or reaſon to exact it in tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ths which are obſcure to us, and the Knowledge of them is aboue our merit and capacity. Such are, not only the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:184324:81"/>of our Faith, but the Diuine reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of them, or (vvhich is the ſame) Gods communication of his thoughts and Councells to ſuch ſlaues and pittifull Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as we are. Chriſt told the Apoſtles, (Ioan. 15.) he <hi>called them his friends, becauſe he communicated to them all vvhich he had heard from his Father.</hi> And euery Catholik Knowes that Gods friendship or fauor is a ſupernatural gift which human nature could not expect as due to it. We haue no right or reaſon therfore to exact or expect that God would not haue us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue whatſoeuer the Church propoſeth with moral euidence as being reuealed by him, unleſs wee ſee the Diuine reuelation applyd to that propoſal by cleer and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſiue euidence; Moral euidence is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to damn us if we deny to proceed therupon in order to a moſt certain (though not cleer) aſſent of the truth of the myſtery,
<note place="margin">(Marc. vlt.)</note> as well as of the exiſtence of the revelation.</p>
               <p>As for what you ſay concerning the nature of Tradition, viz. that it may with concluſiue euidence manifeſt and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrat (if the diſpute be managed by a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty man) an infallible and cleer conne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion with the Diuine reuelation of the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:184324:81"/>Roman Catholik Faith, becauſe it leads us from age to age, and yeare to yeare up along to Chriſt, who is God, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acht our Faith, to this I anſwer two things. 1. That the Tradition of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholik Church (whether we ſpeake of it as it is a Congregation of Knowing and honeſt men, before we believe or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it aſſiſted by the holy Ghoſt, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we ſpeake of it euen after we ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it to be ſo aſſiſted) it can not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrat or proue by concluſiue euiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce that God reuealed any one article of our Catholik Faith, though it may proue by concluſiue euidence that Chriſt did; becauſe that Tradition only proues that Chriſt ſayd he was God, and that the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles belieued ſo, but goes no further in prouing Chriſts Diuinity than by teſtifying his Miracles, which do not demonſtrat, or euidently conclude his Diuinity, though they demonſtrat our obligation of belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing it. 2. I anſwer that though Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doth not demonſtrat or euidently conclude Chriſts Diuinity, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence can not demonſtrat or cleerly conclude that his reuelation of our Faith was Diuine, yet it is a concluſiue argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>ad hominem</hi> againſt Proteſtants and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:184324:82"/>all who confeſs Chriſts Diuinity, that God reuealed all the articles of the Roman Catholik Church, becauſe they confeſs Chriſt is God. And in this ſenſe the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the ſure footing, of Faith vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, &amp;c. argues unanſwerably againſt his Aduerſaries for the concluſiue euidence (by virtue of Tradition) of Gods reueal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (ſuppoſing Chriſt to be God) euery article of the Roman Catholik Faith. And therfore ſeing he hath (as I am credibly informed) thus explaind himſelf, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerues rather great commendation than that ſeuere Cenſure which the Author <hi>of Religion and Gouernment</hi> giues of his doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trin, thinking he agreed with Manicheans and Proteſtants in making cleer euidence the motiue and rule of Chriſtian belief. For, the Author of <hi>ſure footing</hi> utterly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauowes and abhorres as leading to He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy and Atheiſm this Propoſition (which ſom imagined he maintained, as following out of his Principles.) <hi>No Catholik, or at leaſt no learned or vvitty perſon is bound to aſſent or belieue vvith Chriſtian Faith any article the Catholik Church propoſeth as reuealed by God, unleſs it be demonſtrated,</hi> or concluded by cleer and euident reaſon, that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed the ſame article.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:184324:82"/>
               <p>Q. Do not ſom Catholik Diuines teach that cleer Euidence of the Reuelation is conſiſtent vvith our Catholik Faith?</p>
               <p>A. No. Som of them teach the Angels before their fall, and Adam in the ſtate of innocency had (and euen the Deuils now haue) euidence that it was God who reuealed to them the ſupernatural Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries they belieued, and few extend this priuilege to the Prophets and Apoſtles inſpired immediatly by God without out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward preaching.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>See Fr. Dominic. Bannes</hi> 2.2 <hi>q.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>a.</hi> 1. <hi>Eſtius in</hi> 4. <hi>lib. Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>diſt.</hi> 23. <hi>paragr.</hi> 6.</note> But not any one Diuine I could ſee, or heare of, ſayes that cleer euidence of God reuealing our Catholik Faith, (which according to Saint Paul. Rom. 10. coms by hearing <hi>(Fides ex auditu)</hi> and the <hi>preaching</hi> or teſtimony of the Church) is conſiſtent with the ſame.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>OF THE DIFFERENCE BETVVEN certainty ſprung from the ſight of Truth; and certainty grounded upon Truſt. The later, excludes cleer enidence of the truth; and is the certainty required in Chriſtian Faith.</head>
               <p>Q. I find it uery reaſonable (if poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) all men should belieue with the greateſt aſſurance and certainty imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:184324:83"/>that God reuealed euery article both great and ſmale which the Church doth propoſe as reuealed by him, though there were no cleerer euidence than moral for ſuch a reuelation. But how is it poſſible that ſcrupulous and acute Wits, or Doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, can aſſent to Gods reuealing the arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Chriſtianity, or to any truth, with greater aſſurance then there is appearance and euidence of the ſame? Is not euidence and aſſurance (or certainty) the ſame thing in our intellectual aſſents? At leaſt are they not ſo connected with one an other, that they can not be ſeparated, or one be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the other?</p>
               <p>A. Any thing which is uery reaſonable, muſt be poſſible, becauſe reaſon can not lead to, or approue of an impoſſibility. How poſſible and feaſible it is to aſſent with infallible aſſurance and the greateſt certainty (for ſo we muſt aſſent in matters of Faith) with only moral euidence, is cleer in the ſcriptures eſpecialy Iohn. 20. where Chriſt our Sauior reprehended St Thomas for not belieuing with the aſſurance and certainty of Diuine Faith the myſtery of the Reſurrection, though he had but moral euidence for it (the teſtimony of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, not as yet confirmed in grace) Chriſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:184324:83"/>alſo (Marc. ult.) reproacht with obſtinacy and incredulity againſt Faith the Apoſtles themſelues, for not being content with that ſole moral euidence of the Reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which they had from the teſtimony of the three <hi>Maries,</hi> and the two Diſciples of <hi>Emaus.</hi> And certainly Chriſt would not find fault with St Thomas or the Apoſtles, for not doing an impoſſibility. Its poſſible therfore to belieue by an aſſent of Faith with more aſſurance and certainty then there is appearance of the truth, or euiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of the Reuelation.</p>
               <p>I confeſs it is uery difficult to shew how this is don. But if wee diſtinguish the <hi>aſſuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce</hi> or <hi>certainty</hi> we haue of truth by <hi>ſeing</hi> the truth in itſelf, from the aſſurance or cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty we haue therof, by putting our <hi>truſt</hi> in an other, or relying upon his knowledge and integrity, we shall find this point much more eaſy then hitherto hath appeard to moſt both Diuines and Philoſophers. The <hi>aſſurance</hi> and <hi>certainty</hi> of our intellectual aſſents which is produced by the ſight ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther intellectual or ſenſual of the <hi>Truth</hi> it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, inuolues cleer euidence therof. But the <hi>aſſurance</hi> and <hi>certainty</hi> of the Truth, which is an effect of the Truſt and eſteem we haue of an others Veracity, integrity,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:184324:84"/>power and wiſdom, is ſo farr from inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a cleer ſight or euidence of the truth, that it excludes it. For, <hi>Truſt</hi> is no more conſiſtent with our exacting the poſſeſſion, ſight, or cleer euidence of that vvherwith vve truſt an other, than it is vvith doubts, cautions, and ſuſpitions of his integrity or power. Vpon this notion and the true na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Truſt</hi> (excluding ſight or cleer eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the thing truſted) is grounded that ſaying. <hi>Ile truſt ſuch a man no further than I ſee him,</hi> that is, I vvill not truſt him at all.</p>
               <p>This ſuppoſed, We may eaſily compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend how its poſſible to belieue, or to aſſent by an act of our Chriſtian Faith with more aſſurance then appearance, or eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence either of the truth, or of the Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Reuelation. Becauſe <hi>to belieue,</hi> or to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent by an act of our Chriſtian Faith, is to truſt God for his reuelation as well as for the truth reuealed (for we belieue God did reueal the myſtery and ſo we muſt truſt him for the reuelation alſo.) But if we ſee the reuelation euidently applied to the myſtery reuealed, we can not truſt him for either, ſeing the truth of the myſtery is inſeparable, and neceſſarily connected with Gods reuelation therof: and we
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:184324:84"/>can not truſt God for the truth of one of two things that vve know are neceſſarily connected, unleſs vve truſt him for both. Therfore if the reuelation be cleerly eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to us by Tradition, vve can not truſt God for it, nor for the truth of the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery we know is neceſſarily connected therwith.</p>
               <p>Hence doth follow, 1. that ſeing vve can not truſt God for the truth of the myſtery reuealed, unleſs vve truſt him alſo for the reuelation, vve can not belieue either, or any thing the Catholik Church propoſeth as matter of Faith, if vve exact for that belief concluſiue and cleer euidence that God reuealed the ſame. It followeth. 2. That by exacting cleer or concluſiue eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Reuelation to belieue the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery or matter propoſed by the Church, we do not only miſtruſt Gods veracity and goodneſs, but preferr the vvord and veracity of euery honeſt man before his as it is propoſed to us by the Church. For, vvhen vve heare any honeſt man ſpeak, though vvee do not ſee the truth of his vvords, nor any thing elſe neceſſarily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nected vvith that truth, yet vve belieue him, and take his bare vvord for our aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and aſſurance of the truth. But vve
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:184324:85"/>will not take Gods word deliuered to us by the Church, unleſs vve ſee his reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is neceſſarily connected with the truth of the myſtery propoſed. And in this conſiſts moſt of the obſtinacy and malice of Hereſy.</p>
               <p>It followeth 3. That the obſtinacy of Hereſy is not alwayes grounded upon the paſſion or inclination of men to ſenſual pleaſures and thoſe nices which Chriſtian Faith shocks, and condemns; but takes its riſe alſo from the difficulty we find in aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to any thing without euidence, or in truſting, euen God, for the truth of things vvhich ſeem to be unlikely. Chriſts Reſurrection vvas a thing much deſired by Saint Thomas, and the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and by conſequence they vvere wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling enough to belieue it: And yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they thought it an unlikely matter, St Thomas vvould not belieue the other Apoſtles, nor theſe the Diſciples of Emaus and the three Maries, vvhen they aſſured them Chriſt vvas reſuſcitated. And this is the reaſon why there haue bin ſo many ſpeculatiue hereſies, as that of the Arrians againſt Chriſts <hi>conſubſtantiality;</hi> and that of the Greekes againſt the proceſſion of the holy Ghoſt, &amp;c. True it is that the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:184324:85"/>Lutheran and other modern Hereſies haue their principal ſource from ſenſual plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and lendneſs of life; yet no liberty is more bewitching then that of opining, euen in ſpeculation: and therfore the Church hath bin troubled with confuting many ſpeculatiue hereſies in former ages.</p>
               <p>I conclude this Appendix with this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſment, that many miſtakes among Controuerſors are occaſioned by their not being vvell grounded in School Diuinity, eſpecialy in that part of it which treates of the Nature of Faith and Hereſy. Som confound the Motiues of <hi>Faith</hi> vvith the Motiues of <hi>Credibility,</hi> as they do the eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of theſe vvith that of the Diuine Reuelation, and the euidence of this with that of our obligation to belieue it: and fancy that the Authors who pretend to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrat Chriſtianity, or the truth of the Roman Catholik Religion, intend to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrat God reuealed thoſe myſteries and doctrin; vvheras they go no further than to endeauor to demonſtrat the reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs and obligation of belieuing the ſame, by the euidence of the Motiues of <hi>credibility.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some of late (as Fisher, Rushworth, and others in England) haue attempted to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:184324:86"/>demonſtrat or cleerly conclude the euiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of the Diuine reuelation by the certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the human Tradition of the Church, and therupon ground the certainty of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Faith. As their zeal is to be commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, ſo they are to be aduertiſed, that the certainty of Faith muſt be ſupernatural, and by conſequence muſt haue a higher and more infallible <hi>Motiue</hi> than the eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of human Tradition grounded upon that of our ſenſes; as all Diuines confeſs and euen theſe modern Authors ſeem to grant. I heare a bold Spaniard went fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and pretends that Chriſtian Faith is <hi>ſcience,</hi> becauſe the reuelation is euidently concluded from the <hi>Motiues</hi> of <hi>credibility,</hi> Miracles, &amp;c. and becauſe St Paul ſayes, <hi>Scio cui credidi, &amp; certus ſum.</hi> This is but a Spanish conceit. Perhaps Saint Paul in his rapt to the third Heauen might haue eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the Diuine Reuelation. But vve heare of no others that went ſo far to find out that knowledge. I ſee there are <hi>Eſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bars</hi> and <hi>Dianas</hi> in ſpeculatiue Theology, as vvell as in <hi>Moral;</hi> and I think ſpecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiue errors are more dangerous than large caſes of conſcience; becauſe theſe carry a certain horror and diſcredit a long vvith them; but erroneous ſpeculations,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:184324:86"/>if new, ſeem to vulgar comprehenſions (eſpecialy of the weaker ſex) to ſauor of wit; and many would fain ſeem witty upon any ſcore, euen in matters of Faith, wherin the greateſt wits muſt ſubmit to authority, and be commanded by the vvill (piouſly affected, and ſupernaturaly aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted) to belieue more than we ſee, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend.</p>
               <p>Yet the Spaniard is conſequent enough in his error, by ſaying <hi>Faith is ſcience.</hi> For, if it be euident that whatſoeuer God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed is true; and it be euident that God reuealed the Trinity, or Tranſubſtantiation, it muſt needs be euident (and by conſequ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence <hi>Science</hi>) that theſe myſteries are true; and therfore no man who penetrats theſe termes can deny their Truth. For my part, I wish this opinion were true; it would be a great eaſe to all Catholiks vvho find much difficulty in belieuing the articles of Faith. So that the Authors and Abettors of Traditionary euidence haue this aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of their Aduerſaries, that we deſire they may haue the better of us in this Diſpute; and if they haue not, it muſt be want of Reaſon on their ſide, not any preiudice or obſtinacy on ours. But vve haue this aduantage of them, that we may
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:184324:87"/>with more eaſe conuince heretiks (euen the wittieſt) of hereſy and obſtinacy than they can: becauſe its eaſier to demonſtrat or euidently conclude that a man is bound to bilieue God reuealed a myſtery of Faith, than it is to demonſtrat or euidently conclude he did actualy reueale it (as it is eaſier to proue you are bound to belieue this man is your Father, than that realy he is ſo.) And if we conclude euidently the firſt we convince the wittieſt Diffenters or Diſputers in the world, of hereſy and obſtinacy, if they do not ſubmit their iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and belief to that of the Church.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:184324:87"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
